<?xml-model href="tei-epidoc_modified.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Metaphysics vol.1</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Digital Edition</edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editors</resp>
                    <name>Jun Ogawa</name>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <ab/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>     
        <div xml:id="01">
<ab xml:id="001" ref="327a1">[**327 A—328 B** *Socrates describes how he visited the Piraeus in company with Glauco, and was induced by Pole- marchus and others to defer his return to Athens*.] Socrates describes how he visited the Piraeus in company with Glauco, and was induced by Polemarchus and others to defer his return to Athens.</ab>
<ab xml:id="002" ref="327a1">[**327 A 1 κατέβην κτλ.**] Diony. Hal. *de comp. verb*. p. 208 (Reiske) ὁ δὲ Πλά- των, τοὺς ἑαυτοῦ διαλόγους κτενίζων καὶ βοστρυχίζων, καὶ πάντα τρόπον ἀναπλέκων, οὐ διέλιπεν ὀγδοήκοντα γεγονὼς ἔτη. πᾶσι γὰρ δὴ που τοῖς φιλολόγοις γνώριμα τὰ περὶ τῆς φιλοποσίας τἀνδρὸς ἱστορούμενα, τά τ᾽ ἄλλα, καὶ δὴ καὶ τὰ περὶ τὴν δέλτον ἣν τελευτήσαντος αὐτοῦ λέγουσιν εὑρεθῆναι ποικίλως μετακειμένην τὴν ἀρ- χὴν τῆς πολιτείας ἔχουσαν τήνδε “κατέ- βην χθὲς εἰς Πειραιᾶ μετὰ Γλαύκωνος τοῦ Ἀρίστωνος.”\n\nSee also Quint. VIII 6. 64, and Diog. Laert. III 37. The latter gives as his authorities Euphorion and Panaetius. As Cicero was tolerably fa- miliar with the writings of Panaetius, it is possible that he too has the same story in view in *de Sen*. V 13, where he says of Plato “*scribens est mortuus*.” The anecdote may well be true, but does not of course justify any inference as to the date of composition of the Republic. See Introd. § 4.</ab>
<ab xml:id="003" ref="327a2">[**2 τῇ θεῷ.**] What goddess? Bendis or Athena? The festival is the Bendideia (354 A) and it is perhaps safest to acqui- esce in the usual view that Bendis is here meant. “*Alii Minervam intelligunt, quae vulgo ἡ θεὸς appellabatur; neque mihi videtur Socrates in ista Panathenaeorum propinquitate de Minerva veneranda cogi- tare non potuisse : sed quod simpliciter τὴν ἑορτὴν dicit, numina diversa statuere non sinit*” (Schneider).\n\nWe hear of a temple of Bendis in the Piraeus in 403 B.C. (τὴν ὁδὸν ἣ φέρει πρὸς τε τὸ ἱερὸν τῆς Μουνυχίας Ἀρτέμιδος καὶ τὸ Βενδίδειον Xen. *Hell*. II 4. 11). See also Introd. § 3 and App. I.</ab>
<ab xml:id="004" ref="327a3">[**3 νῦν πρῶτον.**] Perhaps 410 B.C. Introd. § 3.</ab>
<ab xml:id="005" ref="327a5">[**5 οἱ Θρᾷκες.**] Probably resident aliens (as opposed to the ἐπιχώριοι or natives), living for commercial purposes in the Piraeus, which at all times contained a large admixture of foreign population. It was part of Athenian policy to en- courage commercial settlers by allowing them to exercise their own cults (Foucart *des assoc. relig. chez les Grecs* p. 131). Foucart holds that the worship of the Thracian goddess Bendis was brought to the Piraeus by Thracian merchants (p. 84). Others have supposed that οἱ Θρᾷκες refers to envoys from Thrace, or Thracian mer- cenaries, the survivors of those who came to Athens in 414 B.C. (Thuc. VII 27); but the other view is more probable.</ab>
<ab xml:id="006" ref="327b1">[**327 B 6 τὸ ἄστυ** or **ἄστυ**] 327 C is regular for Athens itself as opposed to the Piraeus. Hartman would omit the article (cf. Lys. 13. 88 τοὺς ἐν ἄστει οἱ ἐν τῷ Πειραιεῖ); but it occurs infra 328 C, Phaedr. 230 C, Arist. *Pol. Ath.* 38. 1 and elsewhere.</ab>
<ab xml:id="007" ref="327b6">[**10 αὐτός:**] *ipse* ‘erus’ ‘the master’ as often: cf. e.g. Prot. 314 D οὐ σχολὴ αὐτῷ and the Pythagorean αὐτὸς ἔφα. With the deictic οὗτος cf. Symp. 175 A Σωκράτης οὗτος—ἕστηκεν, ‘there goes Socrates—standing.’</ab>
<ab xml:id="008" ref="327c10">[**327 C 18 ἐν λείπεται.**] See cr. n. ἐλλείπεται (which Hermann and others retain) is less pointed, in view of the two alternatives ἢ—κρείττους γένοιτο ἢ μὴ μέ- νειν. For λείπεται said of the μεταξύ cf. (Symp. 202 A) or third alternative, cf. Theaet. 188 A ἄλλο γ᾽ οὐδὲν λείπεται περὶ ἕκαστον πλὴν εἰδέναι ἢ μὴ εἰδέναι.</ab>
<ab xml:id="009" ref="327c14">[**20 ὡς—διανοεῖσθε:**] ‘well, you may make up your mind that we shall refuse to listen.’ Cf. (with Stallbaum) Crat. 439 C διανοηθέντες—ὡς ἰόντων ἁπάντων ἀεὶ καὶ ῥεόντων. μή is owing to the imperative: cf. Soph. *O. C.* 1154 and Jebb’s note.</ab>
<ab xml:id="010" ref="328a1">[**328 1 λαμπὰς κτλ.**] λαμπάς was the official name for a torch-race: see Mommsen *Heortologie* pp. 170 n., 282. τῇ θεῷ: see on 327 A and App. I.</ab>
<ab xml:id="011" ref="328e3 328e4">[**328 E 30 τραχεῖα καὶ χαλεπὴ κτλ.**] The language (as Ast observes) is per- haps suggested by Hesiod *OD*. 290 ff. *μακρὸς δὲ καὶ ὄρθιος οἶμος ἐς αὐτήν | καὶ τρηχὺς τὸ πρῶτον· ἐπὴν δ᾽ ἐς ἄκρον ἵκηται, | ῥηϊδίη δὴ ἔπειτα πέλει, χαλεπὴ περ ἐοῦσα*. Cf. Il. 364 D n.</ab>
<ab xml:id="012" ref="328e6">[**33 ἐπὶ γήραος οὐδῷ.**] The phrase oc- curs first in the *Iliad* (XXII 60, XXIV 487) to denote the natural limit of the life of man. Cephalus is *μάλα πρεσβύτης* 328 B. The same meaning suits also in *Od*. XV 246 (*οὐδ᾽ ἵκετο γήραος οὐδῷ*) 348 and XXIII 212, Hymn. *Aphr*. 106, Hes. *OD*. 331, Hdt. III 14 and elsewhere. Leaf can hardly (I think) be right in explaining *οὐδῷ* as = *ὁδῷ* in Il. XXII 60. *γήραος* is a descriptive genitive (like *τέλος γήραος ἀργαλέον* Mimn. *Fr*. 2. 6, *τοῦ λόγου ἐν δόλιχον*—not *δόλιχον*—*τοῦ λόγου* Prot. 329 A), old age being itself the threshold by which we leave the House of Life. We enter as it were by one door and pass out by another. The idea underlying the phrase may be compared with Democritus’s *κόσμος σκη- νῇ, ὁ βίος πάροδος*· *ἦλθες, εἶδες, ἀπῆλθες* (Mullach *Fr*. Phil. Gr. I p. 356).</ab>
<ab xml:id="013" ref="328e5 328e6 328e7">[**χαλεπὸν κτλ.**] *χαλεπὸν* is neuter on account of *τοῦτο* in 8 *τί σοι φαίνεται τοῦτο*, and *τοῦ βίου* is a simple partitive geni- tive: cf. Xen. *Mem*. I 6. 4 *ἐπισκεψώμεθα τί χαλεπὸν ἥσθησαι τοῦμοῦ βίου*. I can- not agree with Tucker in rendering ‘dis- agreeable in respect of the sort of life.’ Ast takes *χαλεπὸν* as masc. (comparing cases like III 416 B *τὴν μεγίστην τῆς εὐλαβείας*), but afterwards says that he is wrong. Trans- late simply ‘whether it is a painful period of life.’ It is needless to insert (with Hartman) *ἢ οὕτω χαλεπόν*: still worse is Liebhold’s addition of *τέλος*.</ab>
<ab xml:id="014" ref="328e7">[**34 ἐξαγγέλλεις:**] like the *ἐξάγγελος* in tragedy, Cephalus is the bearer of news from behind the scenes.</ab>
<ab xml:id="015" ref="329a3 329a4 329a5 329a6 329a7">[**329 A — 329 D** *Cephalus delivers his views on old age. It is, or should be, a haven of peace; old men have themselves to blame if they are miserable*.] Cephalus delivers his views on old age. It is, or should be, a haven of peace; old men have themselves to blame if they are miserable.</ab>
<ab xml:id="016" ref="329a3">[**329 A 3 παροιμίαν.**] *ἥλιξ ἥλικα* *τέρπει* (Phaedr. 240 C).</ab>
<ab xml:id="017" ref="329a3">[**4 ξυνιόντες:**] i.q. *ὅταν ξυνίωσιν* ‘when- ever they come together.’ Such a use of the participle is admissible when the main verb is in the present of habitual action. *ξυνιόντες* is a needless conjecture.</ab>
<ab xml:id="018" ref="329a7">[**8 οὐδὲ ζῶντες.**] Soph. *Ant*. 1165—1167 *τὰς γὰρ ἡδονὰς | ὅταν προδῶσιν ἄνδρες, οὐ τίθημ᾽ ἐγὼ | ζῆν τοῦτον, ἀλλ᾽ ἔμψυχον ἡγοῦμαι νεκρόν*. Cf. also Mimn. *Fr*. 1. 1 ff.; Sim. *Fr*. 71 *τίς γὰρ ἀδονὰς ἄτερ θανάτων βίος ποθεινός*: Eur. *Fr*. 1065. Similar sentiments are very common throughout Greek literature, especially in poetry.</ab>
<ab xml:id="019" ref="329c1 329c2">[**329 C 16 ἔτι—συγγίγνεσθαι.**] These words are rejected by Hirschig, Cobet, and Hartman, but their genuineness is sup- ported by the singular αὐτὸ in αὐτὸ ἀπέ- φυγον and by Plut. *περὶ φιλοπλουτίας* 5. 525 A Σοφοκλῆς ἐρωτηθεὶς εἰ δύναται γυναικὶ πλησιάζειν, Εὐφήμει, ἄνθρωπε, εἶπεν κτλ. In such matters Greek realism called a spade a spade. In spite of the anecdote here told, few writers have painted sadder pictures of old age than Sophocles: see for example O. C. 1235— 1238 and *Fr*. 684. More in keeping with the present passage is *Fr*. 688 οὐκ ἔστι γῆρας τῶν σοφῶν, ἐν οἷς ὁ νοῦς | θεία ξύνεστιν ἡμέρα τεθραμμένος.</ab>
<ab xml:id="020" ref="329c3 329c4">[**17 ἀπέφυγον—ἀποφυγών.**] The repe- tition adds a certain impressiveness to the sentence. Herwerden is in error when he ejects ἀποφυγών, which seems to have been read also by Plutarch (referred to in last note).</ab>
<ab xml:id="021" ref="329c7">[**21 κατατείνουσαι**] is intransitive. If the meaning were (as Ast holds) transitive —man being conceived as the puppet of the desires *cf. Laws* 644 E—we should expect ἐπὶ- or συν- rather than κατα- τείνουσαι: see Phaed. 94 C and 98 D.</ab>
<ab xml:id="022" ref="329c6 329c8">[**παντάπασιν κτλ.**] The impressive iteration is in keeping with the age and earnestness of the speaker: *cf*. 331 A, B.</ab>
<ab xml:id="023" ref="329c4 329c5">[**22 ἔστι.**] Stallbaum and others eject this word, but it is not easy to see why a scribe should have inserted it, particu- larly in such an idiomatic position. The asyndeton before δεσποτῶν is regular in explanatory clauses. I read ἔστι (with A) in preference to ἔστι: the meaning ‘is pos- sible’ does not suit, and would require ἀπαλλαγῆναι rather than ἀπηλλάχθαι. Translate ‘it is the deliverance once and for all from tyrants full many and furious.’ The grammatical subject, as in English, remains vague; it is involved in ἐπειδὰν —χαλάσωσιν. For the use of ἔστι *cf*. *Euthyphr*. 2 D φαίνεται μοι—ἄρχεσθαι ὀρθῶς· ὀρθῶς γὰρ ἔστι τῶν νέων πρότερον ἐπιμεληθῆναι. The sentence-accent falls on πολλῶν and μαινωμένων and not on ἔστι. The view of old age presented here recalls the μελέτη θανάτου of the Phaedo.</ab>
<ab xml:id="024" ref="329d4">[**329 D 25 εὔκολοι.**] Like Sophocles himself: ὁ δ’ εὔκολος μὲν ἐνθάδ’, εὔκολος δ’ ἐκεῖ (*Ar. Frogs* 82).</ab>
<ab xml:id="025" ref="330c2">[**330 c 16 διπλῆ ἢ οἱ ἄλλοι.**] The meaning is simply ‘twice as much as the others’: cf. e.g. *Laws* 868 A διπλῆ τῷ βλάβος ἐκτείσαν and 928 A ζημιοῦν— διπλῆ. The ἢ is like ἢ after διπλάσιος, πολλαπλάσιος etc. If διπλῆ meant simply ‘on two grounds,’ it could not be followed by ἢ and we should have to regard ἢ οἱ ἄλλοι as an interpolation. Cephalus ex- presses himself somewhat loosely, as if loving a thing on two grounds, or in two ways, were equivalent to loving it twice as much. ταύτῃ below is defined by the ὥσπερ clause, and is preferred to ὥσπερ, partly in order to correspond to διπλῆ but still more to suit κατὰ τὴν χρείαν. The present passage is through Aristotle (*Eth. Nic.* IV. 2. 1120ᵇ 14, cf. ib. IX. 7. 1168ᵃ 1—3) the source of the proverb about ‘parents and poets.’</ab>
<ab xml:id="026" ref="330c7">[**21 ξυγγενέσθαι:**] ‘to meet’ in social in- tercourse, as in *Ap.* 41 A. ξυγγενέσθαι habitual intercourse, which is not what Plato means to say. With the sentiment cf. *Symp.* 173 C ὅταν μέν τινας περὶ φιλο- σοφίας λόγους ἢ αὐτὸς ποιῶμαι ἢ ἄλλων ἀκούω—ὑπερφυῶς ὡς χαίρω· ὅταν δὲ ἄλλους τῶν πλουσίων καὶ χρηματιστικῶν, αὐτός τε ἀχθομαι ὑμᾶς τε τοὺς ἑταίρους ἐλεῶ, ὅτι οἴεσθε τι ποιεῖν οὐδὲν ποιοῦντες.</ab>
<ab xml:id="027" ref="330d5 330d6">[**330 D 26 ἐπειδάν—τελευτήσειν:**] ‘when a man faces the thought that he must die,’ not (with Jowett) ‘when a man thinks himself to be near death,’ which would be ἐπειδάν τις ἐγγὺς εἶναι οἴηται τοῦ τελευτᾶν, as Herwerden proposes to read (cf. *Laws* 922 C ὅταν ἤδη μέλλειν ἡγώμεθα τελευτᾶν). “*Senum, non iuvenum τὸ οἴεσθαι τελευτήσειν est*” (Hartman): the weakness of old age convinces us at last that we too must die. Cf. Simon. 85. 7—10 θητῶν δ᾽ ὄφρα τις ἄνθος ἔχῃ πολυ- ήρατον ἥβης | κοῦφον ἔχων θυμόν, πόλλ᾽ ἀτέλεστα νοεῖ· | οὔτε γὰρ ἐλπὶς ἔχει γηρασμένον οὔτε θανεῖσθαι, | οὐδ᾽ ὑγιὴς ὅταν ᾖ, φροντὶς ἔχει καμάτου.</ab>
<ab xml:id="028" ref="330d8">[**29 ἀδικήσαντα—διδόναι δίκην.**] Plato is fond of this verbal play: cf. *Euthyph.* 8 B and 8 E τῷ γε ἀδικοῦντι δοτέον δίκην. He who does not render justice in deeds must render justice in punishment: for the tale of justice must be made up. Note that we have here in ἀδικία and δίκη the first casual allusion to the subject of the *Republic*.</ab>
<ab xml:id="029" ref="330e2 330e3 330e4">[**330 E 30 αὐτὸς κτλ.**] αὐτός = *ipse s. ultro* as opposed to οἱ λεγόμενοι μῦθοι. The verb is to be supplied by a kind of zeugma from μᾶλλον τι καθορᾷ αὐτά (i.e. τὰ ἐκεῖ; or rather the predicate is accom- modated to the second alternative. Cf. 344 B *infra* and VIII 553 C. To regard the bodily weakness of old age as in itself the cause of clearer vision of the world beyond may be in harmony with the doctrine of the *Phaedo*, but Cephalus is not represented as a Platonist. Tucker needlessly doubts the text.</ab>
<ab xml:id="030" ref="330e7">[**34 καὶ ἐκ τῶν ὕπνων κτλ.**] καὶ is ‘both,’ not ‘and,’ and balances καὶ ζῇ: ‘many a time, like children, awakes out of sleep in terror and lives in the expecta- tion of ill.’ For ὥσπερ οἱ παῖδες compare *Phaed*. 77 D, E, and for the general senti- ment Arist. *Eth. Nic.* I 13. 1102ᵇ 8–11 ἀργία γάρ ἐστιν ἡ ὕπνος τῆς ψυχῆς ἡ λέγε- ται σπουδαία καὶ φαύλη, πλὴν εἴ πῃ κατὰ μικρὸν διεκνοῦνται τινες τῶν κινήσεων, καὶ ταύτῃ βελτίω γίνεται τὰ φαντάσματα τῶν ἐπιεικῶν ἢ τῶν τυχόντων.</ab>
<ab xml:id="031" ref="331a1 331a6">[**331 A 1 ἡδεῖα—γηροτρόφος:**] ἡδεῖα is suggested by Pindar’s γλυκεῖα, and καὶ ἀγαθή, as presently appears, is not part of the quotation, but goes with ἐλπίς and is added by Plato in contrast to μετὰ κακῆς ἐλπίδος. γηροτρόφος κτλ.: ‘to nurse him in old age as Pindar also says.’ γηροτρόφος is best taken by itself and not with ἀγαθή.</ab>
<ab xml:id="032" ref="331a6">[**5 ἀτάλλοισα κτλ.**] ἀτάλλω is used of rearing children, and helps out the idea of γηροτρόφος: δὶς παῖδες οἱ γέροντες. It is not clear how the fragment is to be arranged, nor to what class of Pindar’s poems it belongs. See Bergk *Poet. Lyr. Gr.*⁴ I p. 452.</ab>
<ab xml:id="033" ref="331a9">[**6 εὖ οὖν—σφόδρα.**] The emphasis is quite in keeping with Cephalus’ age and character; and Hartman is certainly wrong in condemning the clause: cf. 329 C, 331 B.</ab>
<ab xml:id="034" ref="331b2 331b3">[**331 B 10 ὀφείλοντα—θεῷ θυσίας τινάς.**] *Phaed*. 118 A εἶπεν, ὦ δὴ τελευ- ταῖον ἐφθέγξατο, ὦ Κρίτων, ἔφη, τῷ Ἀσ- κληπιῷ ὀφείλομεν ἀλεκτρυόνα· ἀλλὰ ἀπό- δοτε καὶ μὴ ἀμελήσητε. Wealth is in Cephalus’ view the indispensable χορηγία ἀρετῆς.</ab>
<ab xml:id="035" ref="331b6">[**12 ἀλλὰ γε ἐν ἀνθ᾽ ἑνός.**] ἀλλὰ γε is extremely rare in Attic prose: in the</ab>
<ab xml:id="036" ref="331e1">[**331 E 29 ὁ τοῦ λόγου κληρονόμος.**] See on παῖδες ἐκείνου τοῦ ἀνδρός II 368 A.</ab>
<ab xml:id="037" ref="331e3 331e4">[**31 τὰ ὀφειλόμενα—ἔστι.**] Probably some current saying attributed to Simonides: there is nothing like it in his fragments. The words do not profess to be a defi-nition of justice: if they did, τὸ would appear before δίκαιον. It is not likely that Simonides himself explained this particular saying as Polemarchus does, although he would not have disapproved of the explanation. In Xen. *Hier*. II 2 he is represented as saying that tyrants are ἱκανώτατοι—κακῶσαι μὲν ἐχθρούς, σῶσαι δὲ φίλους. The words of Socrates σὺ μέν, ὦ Πολέμαρχε, ἴσως γιγνώσκεις, ἐγὼ δὲ ἀγνοῶ tend to fix the responsi-bility of the explanation on Polemarchus alone. Probably Simonides (if the saying is his) meant no more than that we should ‘render unto Caesar the things which are Caesar’s.’ Plato virtually confesses in 332 B that his interpretation is forced.</ab>
<ab xml:id="038" ref="331e4">[**32 ἔμοιγε:**] said with confidence, as Σιμωνίδῃ γε with emphasis and some mockery: with you one might disagree, but not with Simonides.</ab>
<ab xml:id="039" ref="331e6">[**33 σοφὸς—θεῖος.**] Cf. *Prot*. 315 E. σοφός and θεῖος were fashionable words of praise: in the mouth of Socrates they are generally ironical. Plato’s own connotation of the word θεῖος is given in *Men*. 99 C οὐκοῦν, ὦ Μένων, ἄξιον τούτους θείους καλεῖν τοὺς ἄνδρας, οἵτινες νοῦν μὴ ἔχοντες πολλὰ καὶ μεγάλα κατορ-θοῦσιν ὧν πράττουσι καὶ λέγουσιν; Ὀρθῶς ἂν καλοῖμεν θείους τε, οὓς νῦν δὴ ἐλέγομεν χρησμῳδοὺς καὶ μάντεις καὶ τοὺς ποιητικούς· ἅπαντας· καὶ τοὺς πολιτικοὺς οὐχ ἥκιστα τούτων φαῖμεν ἂν θείους τε εἶναι καὶ ἐνθου-σιάζειν, ἐπίπνους ὄντας καὶ κατεχομένους ἐκ τοῦ θεοῦ, ὅταν κατορθῶσι λέγοντες πολλὰ καὶ μεγάλα πράγματα, μηδὲν εἰδότες ὧν λέγουσι.</ab>
<ab xml:id="040" ref="331e6">[**ἀνήρ.**] I formerly read ἀνήρ, but ἀνὴρ (in the predicate) is satisfactory enough: cf. *Men*. 99 D θεῖος ἀνήρ, φασίν, οὗτος.</ab>
<ab xml:id="041" ref="331e9">[**36 παρακαταθεμένου κτλ.**] Xen. *Cyr*. I 6. 31 ff. καὶ ἐπὶ προφάς (sc. ἐπὶ τῶν ἡμετέρων πραγμάτων γενόμενός ποτε ἀνὴρ διδάσκαλος τῶν παίδων) ταῦτα ἐδίδασκεν ὡς καὶ τοὺς φίλους δίκαιον εἴη ἐξαπατᾶν, ἐπὶ τῷ ἀγαθῷ. *Mem*. IV 2. 17 ff. ὀφροῦν is to be taken with παρακατα-θεμένου and not with ἀπαιτοῦντι.</ab>
<ab xml:id="042" ref="331e3">[**37 καίτοι γε ὀφειλόμενον.**] There is the same dispute about καίτοι γε as about μέντοι γε and ἀλλά γε (see on 329 E, 331 B). καίτοι γε has the best MS authority in its favour here and in IV 440 D: elsewhere in Plato it is not well-attested except in the νοθευόμενοι, where it occurs *Min*. 318 E, *Axioch*. 364 B, 368 E. καίτοι γε is also found occasionally in Aristo-phanes, Xenophon, Aristotle, and the orators: see Blaydes on Ar. *Ach*. 611, and the *Lex. Arist*. Many distinguished critics would emend the idiom everywhere; but the instances are far too numerous for such a drastic policy. The difference be-tween καίτοι ὀφειλόμενον γε που (which Hoefer *de part. Plat*. p. 38 would read) and καίτοι γε ὀφειλόμενον would seem to be that in the former more stress is thrown on the word ὀφειλόμενον, in the latter on τοι. καίτοι γε is ‘and surely’ rather than ‘quamquam’ (as Kugler holds *de part. τοι eiusque comp. ap. Pl. usu* p. 20), cf. IV 440 D n. The periphrasis ὀφειλόμενον—ἔστι is used of course to correspond to τὰ ὀφειλόμενα in E above: such periphrases (the principle of which is explained in *Euthyph*. 9 E ff.) are ex-tremely common in Plato. See W. J. Alexander in *A. J. Ph*. IV pp. 299 ff.</ab>
<ab xml:id="043" ref="332a3 332a4">[**332 A 2 ἀποδοτέον—ἀπαιτοῖ:**] ‘well, but we were not on any account to make restoration at the time when the claimant is’—according to the Greek idiom ‘was’ —‘mad.’ Socrates, as in ὅπερ ἄρτι ἐλέ- γομεν, is appealing to the admissions made by the πατὴρ τοῦ λόγου (in 331 C), as he is justified in doing when address- ing his heir. ὀπότε is not—as τότε shews —the particle of ‘indefinite frequency,’ but stands for ὅτε of the direct: the whole clause τότε ὁπότε τις μὴ σωφρόνως ἀπαιτοῖ is thus in the *oratio obliqua* of self-quotation and exactly corresponds to εἰ μανεὶς ἀπαιτοῖ in 331 C. Madvig’s ἀπαιτεῖ for ἀπαιτοῖ is therefore unneces- sary. Goodwin *MT*. p. 213 explains the optative otherwise, but not (I think) rightly.</ab>
<ab xml:id="044" ref="332a9">[**6 ἀγαθὸν μέν τι δρᾶν sc.**] αὐτούς, for τοῖς φίλοις depends on ὀφείλειν, to which τοὺς φίλους is the subject.</ab>
<ab xml:id="045" ref="332a10">[**μανθάνω—ὅτι.**] ὅτι is ‘because,’ not ‘that,’ as always (I believe) in Plato’s use of this phrase: cf. *Euthyph*. 3 B, 9 B and infra III 402 E, VIII 568 E. For the sentiment cf. (with J. and C.) Xen. *Mem*. IV 2 17 ff.</ab>
<ab xml:id="046" ref="332b6">[**332 B 12 ὀφείλεται δέ.**] See cr. n. In explanatory clauses of this kind δέ and not δέ γε is the correct usage: cf. infra 337 D, 344 A. I therefore follow Bekker in reading δέ.</ab>
<ab xml:id="047" ref="332b8">[**13 προσήκει.**] ὀφειλόμενον has thus been equated with προσῆκον by means of the special cases τὸ τοῖς φίλοις ὀφειλόμενον and τὸ τοῖς ἐχθροῖς ὀφειλόμενον. τὸ προσ- ῆκον is a more general term and is the regular word in classical Greek for ‘proper conduct’ or ‘duty’ (as the Greeks con- ceived it), the Stoic καθῆκον being very rarely used in this sense by good authors.</ab>
<ab xml:id="048" ref="332c1 332c2 332c3">[**332 C—336 A**] The definition is further elucidated down to 333 B: and thereafter Socrates begins to criticise it. In the first place, the definition is made more precise by representing justice as an art, whose business it is to benefit friends and injure foes (332 C, D). The ques- tion is then raised—how does the art of justice do good to friends and harm to foes? By the analogy of other arts is Pole-marchus induced to say that justice benefits friends and harms enemies (1) by fighting with them and against them in time of war, and (2) in connexion with partnerships concerned with money in time of peace (332 D—333 B). The explanation of Simonides’ saying is now complete. Socrates first directs his attack against (2). In cases where money has to be used, it is not justice, but some other art, that is useful for the required purpose: in other words justice is (in time of peace) useful only in dealing with useless or unused money and other unused objects: which is an unworthy view of the art (333 B— 333 E). Further, the analogy of the other arts shews that the art of justice, if it is the art of keeping money safe, is also the art of stealing money—always provided that it does so for the benefit of friends and the injury of foes (333 E—334 B). Po- lemarchus, in bewilderment, reiterates his</ab>
<ab xml:id="049" ref="333b7 333b10">[**333 B 10 εἰς τίνα δὴ κοινωνίαν**] is idiomatic for εἰς τίνος δὴ κοινωνίαν. Compare VIII 556 C ἡ ἐν ὁδῶν πορείαις ἡ ἐν ἄλλαις τισὶ κοινωνίαις and τὴν τιμὴν ταύτην (where the English idiom would expect τὴν τιμὴν ταύτης) in II 371 E. In spite of εἰς κρουμάτων and εἰς ἀργυρίου, it is not necessary to read (with Richards) τίνος.</ab>
<ab xml:id="050" ref="333c7">[**333 C 18 παρακαταθέσθαι καὶ σῶν εἶναι.**] The double expression is necessary to explain κοινῇ χρῆσθαι: the κοινωνία arises because one deposits the money and by the other it is kept safe.</ab>
<ab xml:id="051" ref="333c11">[**20 ἄχρηστον—χρήσιμος.**] ἄχρηστος fluctuates between 'unused' and 'useless'; the latter sense is predominant here and gives an epigrammatic tone to the sentence (cf. ἐν μὲν χρήσει ἄχρηστος, ἐν δὲ ἀχρηστίᾳ χρήσιμος in D). It is noticeable that Plato does not take into account the possibility of money being deposited at interest: in this case the money could not be said to be useless.</ab>
<ab xml:id="052" ref="333d4">[**333 D 22 καὶ κοινῇ καὶ ἰδίᾳ:**] not 'to the individual and to the state,' but 'both in dealings with others, and in personal concerns.' The words καὶ ἰδίᾳ are, strictly speaking, irrelevant, for it is with κοινωνήματα (in the widest sense) that we are concerned. They are to be regarded merely as a rhetorical amplification for the sake of emphasis: cf. infra 350 A, 351 A nn.</ab>
<ab xml:id="053" ref="333e1 333e2">[**333 E 28 οὐκ ἂν οὖν κτλ.**] See cr. n. Some may think that we should read οὐκοῦν (with the majority of Mss) and cancel εἴη after σπουδαῖον (so also Vind. D), understanding ἐστι. The accidental omission of ἄν is however not uncommon in Plato's MSS : see on IV 437 B.</ab>
<ab xml:id="054" ref="333e4">[**31 οὗτος καὶ φυλάξασθαι.**] Because knowledge of anything implies know- ledge also of its opposite, according to the usual Socratic view. See *Phaed*. 97 D οὐδὲν ἄλλο σκοπεῖν προσήκειν ἀνθρω- πον—ἀλλ᾽ ἢ τὸ ἄριστον καὶ τὸ βέλτιστον· ἀναγκαῖον δὲ εἶναι τὸν αὐτὸν τοῦτον καὶ τὸ χεῖρον εἰδέναι, *Charm*. 166 E, *Hipp. Min*. 367 A ff. See also Stewart's *Notes on the .Nicomachean Ethics* Vol. I p. 378.</ab>
<ab xml:id="055" ref="333e3 333e4 333e6 333e7">[**32 φυλάξασθαι κτλ.**] See cr. n. With the emendation in the text, the argument is as follows: (1) he who can πατάξαι, can φυλάξασθαι: (2) he who can φυλά- ξασθαι (νόσον), can λαθεῖν ἐμποιήσας (νό- σον): (3) he who can κλέψαι (τὰ τῶν πολε- μίων), is a good φύλαξ of an army. Thus the predicate of each step in the argument corresponds to the subject of the step next following: for λαθεῖν ἐμποιήσας (νόσον) is to be taken as parallel to κλέψαι (τὰ τῶν πολεμίων). The argument is unsound, and not intended to be serious: it is enough that it suffices to bewilder Polemarchus. For a further discussion on this passage see App. II.</ab>
<ab xml:id="056" ref="333e7">[**33. ἐμποιήσας**] coniecit Schneider: ἐμποιήσας ΑΠΣ: καὶ ἐμποιήσαι Π2γ.</ab>
<ab xml:id="057" ref="334a4 334a6">[**334 A 1 στρατοπέδου γε κτλ.**] The στρατηγός must be both φυλακτικὸς τε καὶ κλεπτικὸς according to Socrates in Xen. *Mem*. III 1. 6.</ab>
<ab xml:id="058" ref="334a6 334a9">[**2 κλέπτειν καὶ κλέμμα**] were used (especially by Spartans) with reference to military operations involving surprise and stealth (Classen on Thuc. V 9. 5).</ab>
<ab xml:id="059" ref="334a9">[**6 κλέπτης—ἀναπέφανται.**] Cf. *Hipp*. *Min*. 365 C ff., where this view is worked out at length, *ib*. 369 B ἀναπέφανται ὁ αὐτὸς ὢν ψευδὴς τε καὶ ἀληθὴς and Xen. *Mem*. IV 2. 20 ff. ἀναπέφανται, as J. and C. remark, expresses an unexpected re- sult—here a paradox. Like ὁ ἐκὼν ἁμαρ- τάνων ἀμείνων, the conclusion is a logical inference from the Socratic identification of virtue and knowledge, made without regard to experience.</ab>
<ab xml:id="060" ref="334b1 334b2">[**334 B 8 ἀγαπᾷ,**] ‘esteems,’ is said with reference to ἐσθλὸν in Hom. *Od*. xix 395 f. μητρὸς ἔης πατέρ᾽ ἐσθλὸν, ὃς ἀνθρώ- πους ἑκάστο | κλεπτοσύνη θ᾽ ὅρκῳ τε. The suggested ἀγαπᾷ for ἀγαπᾷ τε would be too strong. In *Symp*. 180 B μᾶλλον— θαυμάζουσιν καὶ ἀγαπᾷ—ὅταν ὁ ἐρώμενος τὸν ἐραστὴν ἀγαπᾷ, where the meaning of ἀγαπᾷ is shown by οὕτω περὶ πολλοῦ ἐποιεῖτο in 180 A.</ab>
<ab xml:id="061" ref="book334b">[**with εὖ πράττειν e.g.**] *Charm*. 172 A, 173 D, *Alc*. I 116 B, *Arist. Eth. Nic*. I 8. 1098b 20. It is by the analogy of the arts that Socrates in this chapter seeks to prove, first the identification κακῶς ποιεῖν = κακὸν ποιεῖν, and second that the good man cannot harm others: the Socratic con- ception of right conduct as an art is still predominant. It is important to observe that it was by means of this Socratic weapon that Plato achieved this noble anticipation of Christian ethical theory (*St Matth*. 5. 44 al.). Cf. also *Gorg*. 472 D ff.</ab>
<ab xml:id="062" ref="335c1 335c6">[**16 ἀνθρώπους δὲ κτλ.**] Cf. 352 E— 353 E.</ab>
<ab xml:id="063" ref="335e4">[**335 E 33 οὐκ ἦν σοφὸς—εἰπών.**] Teichmüller (*Lit. Fehd*. I p. 22 n.) finds in this an allusion to Xenophon, who puts into the mouth of Socrates (addressing Critobulus in *Mem*. II 6. 35) the words ἔγνωκας ἀνδρὸς ἀρετὴν εἶναι, νικᾶν τοὺς μὲν φίλους εὖ ποιοῦντα, τοὺς δὲ ἐχθροὺς κακῶς: but the reference is only to 331 E σοφὸς γὰρ καὶ θεῖος ἀνήρ. The presents φησίν and νοεῖ are used in a general way, be- cause such a theory and such an interpre- tation of it might be held by any one at any time: ἡ οὐκ ἦν σοφὸς ὁ ταῦτα εἰπών the time is changed to the past to suggest οὐκ ἦν Σιμωνίδης ὁ ταῦτα εἰπών (Simonides being σοφός 331 E). But for ὁ ταῦτα εἰπών, it would be ἔστι. It is a mistake to take ἦν as ‘is after all’: ἦν is hardly so used in Plato without ἄρα, nor is *Phaedr*. 230 A (cited by Goodwin *MT*. p. 13) an example of that idiom.</ab>
<ab xml:id="064" ref="335e7 335e8">[**36 ἐάν τις αὐτὸ φῇ—Σιμωνίδην:**] as Xenophon virtually does in *Hier*. 11 2: see 331 E n.</ab>
<ab xml:id="065" ref="335e9">[**37 τῶν σοφῶν τε καὶ μακαρίων ἀνδρῶν.**] μακάριος is somewhat stronger than θεῖος, which it suggests, μακάρες being a usual epithet of gods. The whole phrase is in- tended to carry us back to 331 E σοφὸς γὰρ καὶ θεῖος ἀνήρ. Ast’s view that μακα- ρύων means “qui ante nostram aetatem floruerunt,” as if ‘sainted,’ misses the al- lusion to 331 E, and is a little far-fetched: it is enough that μακάριος conveys the same ironical commendation as θεῖος: cf. (with Stallbaum) *Men*. 71 A.</ab>
<ab xml:id="066" ref="335e10">[**ἐγὼ γοῦν.**] See *cr. n*. With Hartman, I adopt Bekker’s restoration: cf. VII 527 D. For γοῦν A everywhere writes γοῦν.</ab>
<ab xml:id="067" ref="336a4 336a5">[**336 A † Περιάνδρου κτλ.**] Periander, Xerxes and Perdicas are taken as types of tyrants, and no tyrant is σοφός (*Rep*. IX 587 D). It is noticeable that Peri- ander does not appear in the list of the seven wise men in *Prot*. 343 A. The ex- pedition of Xerxes against Greece is cited by Callicles in *Gorg*. 483 D in connexion with the doctrine that might is right. In Περίδικκον the allusion is to Perdic- cas II, father of Archelaus (*Gorg*. 471 B): he died late in 414 or early in 413, three years before the probable date of action of the *Republic* (*Introd*. § 3), after proving himself a fickle friend and foe to the Athenians during the Peloponnesian war.\n\nIsmenias is mentioned again in *Men*. 90 A as having become rich δόντος τινὸς—ὁ νῦν νεωστὶ εἰληφὼς τὰ Πολυκρά- τους χρήματα. There can be no doubt that he is to be identified with the Isme- nias who (see Xen. *Hell*. III 5. 1) in 395 took money from Timocrates the Rhodian, envoy of the Persian King, in order to stir up war against Sparta, and who in 382, when the Spartans had seized the Cadmea, was condemned on this charge among others (Xen. *Hell*. 2. 35; Plut. *Pelop*. 5. 2). Plato implies that Ismenias kept enough Persian gold to enrich him- self. He was no true Greek if he did not. But what is meant by saying that he had received the money of *Polycrates*? This question has been much discussed. Pos- sibly ‘the money of Polycrates’ (with allu- sion, of course, to the riches of the Samian tyrant) was a sarcastic expression current in Athens for ‘the money of Timocrates’: this is perhaps the more likely as we are informed that the Athenians got no share of it themselves (*Hell*. III 5. 2). Plato would naturally avail himself of such a political gibe to express his dislike of a man who took gold from the natural enemy of Greece (*Rep*. V 470 C) to stir up not war, but sedition (ib. 470 B), and withdraw Agesilaus from fighting with the barbarian: for his political ideal in foreign policy was that of Cimon. See also on V 471 B. It is not however likely, I think, that the present passage was written after Ismenias’ death, for Plato is not given to reviling his contemporaries after their death. That the other three persons cited by Plato were already dead would only make his reproof of the living more marked and scathing. The present passage—so far as it goes—is on the whole in favour of Teichmüller’s view (*Lit. Fehd*. I p. 25) that the first book of the *Republic* was written soon after 395, when the dis- graceful affair was still fresh in men’s minds. See *Introd*. § 4.</ab>
<ab xml:id="068" ref="336a5 336a6">[**5 πλουσίου:**] to be pressed (as in III 395 D, 409 C: cf. IV 431 C): their power is fancied, not real: they cannot even do the thing they want: cf. *Gorg*. 467 A ff. πῶς ἂν οὖν οἱ ῥήτορες μέγα δύναντο ἢ οἱ τύραννοι ἐν ταῖς πόλεσιν, ἐὰν μὴ Σωκράτης</ab>
<ab xml:id="069" ref="book337a">[**337 A—339 B** *After some wrangling, Thrasymachus finally declares justice to be ‘the interest of the stronger.’ Rulers are stronger than those whom they rule; and in every state they pass laws in their own interest: and what is done in their own interest they call just.*] After some wrangling, Thrasymachus finally declares justice to be ‘the interest of the stronger.’ Rulers are stronger than those whom they rule; and in every state they pass laws in their own interest: and what is done in their own interest they call just.</ab>
<ab xml:id="070" ref="book337a">[**337 A ff.**] The natural history defini- tion of justice (ὁ φύσει ὅρος τοῦ δικαίου *Laws* IV 714 C) is here for the first time mentioned in the *Republic*. It is to be noticed that the theory is presented by Thrasymachus not—in the first instance as a rule of conduct for the individual, but as a political theory: his object is to describe the actual practice of Greek states (338 D ff.). We are thus for the first time introduced to the political aspect of δικαιοσύνη. The same view of the definition is taken in *Laws* 714 C ff., and it is the same theory which is afterwards (in II 358 E ff.) represented by Glauco as an hypothesis on which not Thrasymachus only but many others (Θρασυμάχου καὶ μυρίων ἄλλων 358 E) explained the origin and constitution of existing states: cf. also *Gorg*. 483 A ff. We are therefore justified in supposing that the definition which Plato puts into the mouth of Thrasymachus represents a theory current in the politics of the day. The conduct of Athens to- wards her allies furnished many examples of the practical application of this rule of government; and, if we may trust Thu- cydides, similar principles were frankly laid down by Athenian statesmen in their speeches: see for example I 76. 2 δεῖ καθεστῶτος τῶν ἥσσω ὑπὸ δυνατωτέρου κατείργεσθαι, and cf. I 77. 4, V 89 and 105. 2 τὸ ἀνθρώπειον σαφῶς διὰ παντὸς ὑπὸ φύσεως ἀναγκαίας οὖν ἂν κρατῇ ἄρχειν. It is indeed not too much to say that ‘Might is Right’ was the only argument by which the existence of the Athenian empire could be defended before the tribunal of Greek public opinion, which regarded the independent πόλις as the only legitimate form of civic life. Hence the dominion of Athens is often in Thu- cydides called a τυραννίς, from which the Spartans claimed to be liberating their τὴν ἀρχήν, 62. 5 ff., IV 85. 6, and cf. Henkel *Studien zur Gesch. d. gr. Lehre vom Staat* pp. 126—128. The most conspicuous assertion of the principle before Plato’s time was found in Pindar’s much-quoted fragment (Bergk 169 and ap. Pl. *Gorg*. 484 B) νόμος ὁ πάντων βασιλεὺς | θνατῶν τε καὶ ἀθανάτων | ἄγει δικαιῶν τὸ βιαιότατον | ὑπερτάτᾳ χειρὶ κτλ., though it may well be doubted (with Dümmler *Prolegomena zu Platon’s Staat* p. 34) whether Pindar intended to suggest any such view. It is in order to refute this theory, as expounded by Glauco and Adimantus, Thrasymachus’ successors in the argument (see on παῖδες ἐκείνου τοῦ ἀνδρός II 368 A) that Socrates finds it necessary to draw a picture of an Ideal State (ib. 368 C ff.), so that the political theory of Plato’s *Republic* may truly be said to commence here. For more on this subject see Chiappelli *Per la storia della Sofistica Greca* in *Archiv f. Gesch. d. Philos*. III pp. 265 ff.</ab>
<ab xml:id="071" ref="337a2">[**3 σαρδάνιον.**] Plato uses this expres- sion as Homer does, of a sinister smile which bodes pain to others: *Od*. xx 301 f. μείδησε δὲ θυμῷ | σαρδάνιον μάλα τοῖον (of Odysseus among the suitors). Among later authors it more frequently denotes the forced smile which disguises the sufferer’s own pain; and so apparently Simonides used the phrase (*Fr*. 202 A Bergk). The explanations volunteered by the ancients apply only to the non-Homeric usage: the Scholiast, however, at the end of his note on this passage correctly re- marks, μήποτε οὖν τὸ Ὁμηρικόν, ὅθεν καὶ ἡ παροιμία ἴσως ἐρρύη, “μείδησε δὲ κτλ.,” τὸν ἀπ’ αὐτῶν τῶν χειλέων γέλωσια καὶ μέχρι τοῦ σαρκίου γιγνόμενον σημαίνει. The spelling σαρδόνιον came into vogue through the popular etymology from the bitter Sardinian herb, ἧς οἱ γευσάμενοι δοκοῦσι μὲν γελῶντες, σπασμῷ δὲ ἀποθνήσκουσιν (Schol.). The Scholiast’s suggested deri- vation from σαίρειν (*ringi*, as of an angry dog) suits the meaning which the phrase bears in Homer and Plato, and is pro- bably right. Photius’ σαρδάζων· μετὰ πικρίας γελῶν preserves the δ.</ab>
<ab xml:id="072" ref="337a6">[**6 ποιήσοις**] is rejected by Cobet and Herwerden. “Post οὐδὲν ἄλλο ἤ, τί ἄλλο ἤ, πάντα μᾶλλον ἤ *verbum omittunt*” (says Cobet, quoting Theophr. *Char*. c. 25). ποιήσοις is not however otiose, but sug- gests the phrase πάντα ποιεῖν, ‘leave nothing undone,’ as in *Euthyph*. 8 c πάντα ποιοῦσι καὶ λέγουσι φεύγοντες τὴν δίκην: cf. *Ap*. 39 A.</ab>
<ab xml:id="073" ref="337a6 337a8">[**7 ἐρωτᾷ.**] I formerly read ἐρωτᾷ (with Goodwin *MT*. p. 277). A few inferior MSS have ἔροιτο. The optative is cer- tainly the regular periodic construction in clauses of this kind: but the indicative may perhaps be allowed in loose con- versational style.</ab>
<ab xml:id="074" ref="337b6">[**337 B 15 τυγχάνει ὄν.**] Stallbaum explains ὂν as ‘being true,’ and τι as the subject to τυγχάνει. This view is perhaps less natural than to make ὂν the copula and τι the predicate: for the pronoun ‘it’ i.e. τὸ ἐρωτώμενον (Schneider) can be quite easily understood. For the use of τυγχάνει ὄν (‘really is’) cf. II 379 A, VII 518 E, *Euthyph*. 4 E with my note ad loc.</ab>
<ab xml:id="075" ref="337c2">[**337 C 16 ὡς δή.**] The force of ὡς in this common ironical expression (*quasi vero*, cf. *Gorg*. 468 E, 499 B) is referred by Jebb (*Soph. O. C*. 809) to an ellipse: ‘(do you mean) forsooth that.’ An ob- jection to this theory is that it will not explain ὡς δή τοι in cases like II 366 C, *Phaedr*. 242 C, *Tim*. 26 A. It seems better to explain these usages on the same principle. The view that ὡς is exclamatory will not account for II 366 C and is not specially appropriate in the other places. Neither is it easy to make ὡς=*ἐπεί* (‘your illustration is excellent, seeing that the cases are so very similar!’ Tucker). Schneider (on II 366 C) re- gards ὡς as nearly equivalent to ὥστε (cf. note on II 365 D). Probably ὡς is in reality consequential (like the English ‘so’), the relative retaining its original demonstrative sense. This explanation will, I believe, suit all the passages in question.</ab>
<ab xml:id="076" ref="337d1">[**337 D 23 περὶ δικαιοσύνης κτλ.**] and fallacies which may be employed in rhetorical and dialectical reasoning” (*Aristotle’s Rhetoric Vol. I* p. 17). Cf. *Gorg*. 483 A (cited by Tucker).</ab>
<ab xml:id="077" ref="337d3">[**26 εἴτ᾽ οὐκ οἶσθα κτλ.**] ‘Do you mean to say you don’t know’ etc. The division of constitutions into Monarchy, Oligarchy (for which Aristocracy is here substituted) and Democracy was familiar to everybody: see Aeschin. *Ctes*. 6, *Tim*. 4 ὁμολογοῦνται γὰρ τρεῖς εἶναι πολι- τεῖαι παρὰ πᾶσιν ἀνθρώποις, τυραννὶς καὶ ὀλιγαρχία καὶ δημοκρατία. Cf. Whibley *Greek Oligarchies* pp. 17, 24. Thrasy- machus proceeds to define κρεῖττον as ὁ κρατῶν (not ὁ ἰσχυρότερος, as Socrates had insinuated): -κρατοῦνται in δημο- κρατοῦνται and ἀριστοκρατοῦνται well brings out his meaning. Cf. *Laws* 714 B νόμων εἴδη τινές φασιν εἶναι τοσαῦτα ὅσα- περ πολιτειῶν, and C οὔτε γὰρ πρὸς τὸν πόλεμον οὔτε πρὸς ἀρετὴν ὅλην βλέπειν δεῖν φασι τοὺς νόμους, ἀλλ᾽ ἥτις ἂν καθε- στηκυῖα ᾖ πολιτεία, ταύτῃ δεῖν τὸ συμφέρον ὅπως ἄρξει τε ἀεὶ καὶ μὴ καταλυθήσεται, καὶ τὸν φύσει ὀρθὸν δίκαιον λέγεσθαι κάλλισθ᾽ οὕτως. Πῶς; “Ὅτι τὸ τοῦ κρείτ- τονος συμφέρον ἐστί.</ab>
<ab xml:id="078" ref="338d11">[**29 τίθεται δέ γε:**] *Laws* 1. c. τίθεται δήπου, φασί, τοὺς νόμους ἐν τῇ πόλει ἑκάστοτε τὸ κρατοῦν. ἡ γάρ; ‘Ἀληθῆ λέγεις. Ἀρ᾽ οὖν ὅδε, φασί, ποτὲ δῆμον νικήσαντα ἢ τινα πολιτείαν ἄλλην ἢ καὶ τύραννον θέσθαι ἔκοντα πρὸς ἄλλο τι πρῶτον νόμους ἢ τὸ συμφέρον ἑαυτῷ τῆς ἀρχῆς τοῦ μένειν; Πῶς γὰρ οὔ; Aristotle makes it the distinguishing mark of his three perverted forms (παρεκβάσεις) of consti- tution (τυραννίς, ὀλιγαρχία, δημοκρατία) that they seek their own and not τὸ κοινῇ συμφέρον: *Pol*. Γ 7. 1279ᵇ 4 ff.</ab>
<ab xml:id="079" ref="338e4 338e5">[**338 E 32 τὸν τούτου ἐκβαίνοντα κτλ.**] *Laws* 714 D οὐκοῦν καὶ δὴ ταῦτα τὰ τεθέντα παραβαίνῃ, κολάσει ὁ θέμενος ὡς ἀδικοῦντα, δίκαια ταῦτ᾽ εἶναι ἐπονο- μάζων ‘ἔοικε γοῦν. Ταῦτ᾽ ἄρ᾽ ἀεὶ καὶ οὕτω καὶ ταύτῃ τὸ δίκαιον ἓν ἔχοι. Φησὶ γοῦν οὗτος ὁ λόγος. νόμος and δίκαιον are identified by this theory.</ab>
<ab xml:id="080" ref="339a1">[**339 A 1 ταὐτὸν εἶναι δίκαιον.**] Her- werden would expunge ταὐτὸν but αὐτὸ is not more otiose here than τὸ αὐτὸ below.</ab>
<ab xml:id="081" ref="339b3">[**339 B 10 συμφέρον γέ τι.**] There is here a hint of the main purpose of the Republic, which is to prove that δίκαιον is ξυμφέρον in the truest sense for the individual and the state.</ab>
<ab xml:id="082" ref="bookNoneNone">[**339 B—341 A** *Even if we assume that rulers seek their own ad- vantage, yet they often err, and enact laws to their own disadvantage: therefore, as it is just for subjects to obey their rulers, Justice will sometimes consist in doing what is not the interest of the stronger.* Socrates reiterates this objection and is supported by Polemarchus. It is urged by Clitophon that Thrasymachus meant by ‘the interest of the stronger’ what was thought—whether rightly or wrongly— by the stronger to be to their interest. Thrasymachus declines to avail himself of this suggestion, and explains that, strictly speaking, rulers, *qua* rulers, can- not err. This statement he supports by arguing from the analogy of medical practitioners and others, pleading that his earlier concession was but a popular way of expressing the fact that rulers seem to err. Therefore the original definition was strictly correct. *Justice is the interest of the stronger, since rulers make laws in their own interest, and, *qua* rulers, are infallible.* On the reasoning of Thrasymachus in these two chapters see 341 A *n*.] 339 B-341 A</ab>
<ab xml:id="083" ref="339b8">[**339 B 13 οὐ—μέντοι.**] “In inter- rogationibus haec particula” (μέντοι) “ita cum οὐ negatione coniungitur, ut gravis- sima sententiae vox intercedat, quo modo aliquis eis quae ex altero quaerit summam veritatis ingerit speciem” (Hoefer *de part. Plat.* p. 34). μέντοι is simply ‘of course,’ ‘surely’: ‘surely you regard it as just to obey the rulers, do you not?’ The idiom is frequent in Plato. The other examples of it (cited by Stallbaum) in the Republic are infra 346 A, VII 521 D, IX 581 A, 584 A, X 596 E.</ab>
<ab xml:id="084" ref="339b2 339b3">[**14 πότερον δὲ ἀναμάρτητοι κτλ.**] The reasoning echoes that of 334 C above.</ab>
<ab xml:id="085" ref="339c4 339c5 339c7">[**339 C 17 τιθέναι—τίθεσθαι:**] we should expect τιθέναι in both cases, as the ἄρχοντες according to the theory we are discussing are κρείττονες and supreme as legislators: but the middle of personal interest is naturally used in combination with τὰ ξυμφέροντα ἑαυτοῖς: cf. infra 341 A.</ab>
<ab xml:id="086" ref="339d4">[**339 D 23 τί λέγεις σύ:**] a favourite eristic formula: see Ar. *Clouds* 1174 τοῦτο τοὐπιχώριον | ἀτεχνῶς ἔπαυθει, τὸ τί λέγεις σύ;</ab>
<ab xml:id="087" ref="339d6">[**35 ἀποκρίνεσθαι.**] The imperfect in- finitive, as Schneider remarks (Addit. p. 6).</ab>
<ab xml:id="088" ref="341a1">[**341 A—342 E** *Socrates now meets Thrasymachus on his own ground, and attacks his definition according to the ‘strictest form’ of argument. He shews by analogy that every ruler *qua* ruler seeks the good of those whom he rules, since every art aims at the good of its own *peculium* or object, and not at its own, for *qua* art there is nothing lacking to it*.] Socrates now meets Thrasymachus on his own ground, and attacks his definition according to the ‘strictest form’ of argument. He shews by analogy that every ruler *qua* ruler seeks the good of those whom he rules, since every art aims at the good of its own *peculium* or object, and not at its own, for *qua* art there is nothing lacking to it.</ab>
<ab xml:id="089" ref="book341a">[**341 A ff.**] It is to be noted that the discussion is now transferred from the region of facts into an atmosphere of idealism. For this, Thrasymachus is primarily responsible. The theory that the ruler *qua* ruler makes no mistakes, is no doubt true ideally, but practically it is of little moment, since he will suffer *qua* ruler for the errors which he commits in moments of aberration. The strength of Thrasymachus’ theory lay in its cor- respondence with the facts (real or appa- rent) of experience; it is the temptation to defend his theory against the criticism of Socrates which leads him to abandon facts for ideals; and as soon as he is re- futed on the idealistic plane, he descends to facts again (343 A ff.). The vein of idealism struck by Thrasymachus is worked to some purpose by Socrates. To assert that rulers *qua* rulers always seek the good of their subjects is in reality to set before us a political ideal, and Plato’s Ideal Commonwealth is in- tended to be its embodiment in a state. Plato was probably the first to develop and elaborate this principle of political science, but the legislations of Solon and other early lawgivers furnish examples of its application to practical politics (see especially Arist. *Rep.* ch. 12 and Solon’s verses there cited), and it is formulated by the historical Socrates in Xen. *Mem.* III 2, with which compare Cyrop. VIII 2. 14. See also Henkel *Studien zur Gesch. d. gr. Lehre vom Staat* pp. 44, 145, and Whibley *Greek Oligarchies* p. 11 n. 29.</ab>
<ab xml:id="090" ref="341a6">[**5 συκοφαντεῖν**] is explained in ἐξ ἐπιβουλῆς—κακουργοῦντά σε, where κα- κουργοῦντα (as Schneider observes) is not used as in 338 D of putting an evil or sophistical interpretation on a theory, but of damaging a man’s personal reputation and credit: ‘scilicet existimationis et pecuniae detrimentum facturus sibi vide- batur sophista ideoque Socratem se, quam- quam frustra, impugnare in sequentibus quoque criminatur.’</ab>
<ab xml:id="091" ref="341b1 341b2">[**341 B 9 μὴ λαθών:**] “si non latu- eris” (Schneider). Stephanus conjectured μὴ and Ast for μὴ: but either change would destroy the antithesis between λανθάνειν and βιάζεσθαι—secret guile and open fraud: cf. II 365 D ἀλλὰ δὴ θεοὺς μὲν λανθάνειν, θεοὺς βιάζεσθαι δυνατὸν. Hirschig’s excision of μὴ λαθών greatly impairs the emphasis.</ab>
<ab xml:id="092" ref="341b5">[**12 τὸν ὡς ἔπος εἰπεῖν.**] The only exact parallel to this use of ὡς ἔπος εἰπεῖν in Plato is *Laws* 656 E σκοπῶν δ’ εὑρήσεις αὐτόθι τὰ μυριοστὸν ἔτος γεγραμμένα ἢ τετυπωμένα οὐχ ὡς ἔπος εἰπεῖν μυριοστὸν ἀλλ’ ὄντως*. This idiomatic phrase is rare before Plato, who uses it 77 times with the meaning ‘to put the matter in a word,’ implying that other and possibly more exact means of describing the thing in question might be found. In 52 of these cases the phrase is combined with πᾶς or οὐδείς and their family of words, in the sense of *fere, propemodum*: its use in other connexions is in part a return to old poetic usage; cf. Aesch. *Pers*. 714, Eur. *Hipp*. 1162, Heracl. 167. See Grünenwald in Schanz’s *Beiträge zur hist*. *Synt*. d. gr. Spr. II 3, pp. 21 ff. The other examples in the *Republic* are V 464 D, VIII 551 B, IX 577 C.</ab>
<ab xml:id="093" ref="341b6">[**ὁ νῦν δὴ ἔλεγες:**] viz. in 340 E κατὰ τὸν ἀκριβῆ λόγῳ. The antecedent is the phrase ἀκριβεῖ λόγῳ. The conjecture of Benedictus, ὄν for δ’, though adopted by several editors, would (as Schneider remarks) leave it uncertain whether λόγῳ or τὸν was referred to by the relative. There is no MS authority for ὄν.</ab>
<ab xml:id="094" ref="341c1 341c2">[**341 C 17 εὑρεῖν—λέοντα.**] παροιμία ἐπὶ τῶν καθ’ ἑαυτὸν τι ἢ ἀδύνατα ποιεῖν ἐπι- χειρούντων λεγομένη (Schol.). The pro- verb is very rare, and does not seem to occur elsewhere in classical Greek.</ab>
<ab xml:id="095" ref="341c3">[**18 οὐδὲν ὧν καὶ ταῦτα:**] ‘though you were a nonentity at that too’: i.e. at bluffing me, as well as in other respects. So (I think) Schneider, rightly (“aber auch darin ist’s nichts mit dir”). Others (e.g. Shorey in *A. J. Ph*. xvi p. 234) explain ‘and that too though you are a thing of naught.’ But in that case καὶ ταῦτα would surely precede οὐδὲν ὧν. Tucker can hardly be right in making καὶ ταῦτα simply ‘moreover’ ‘too,’ ‘and proved a failure, too.’ Nor (in spite of J. B. Mayor in *Cl. Rev*. x p. 110) is it quite enough to translate (with Campbell) ‘though here again you are nobody,’ i.e. ‘with as little effect as ever.’</ab>
<ab xml:id="096" ref="341c6 341c7">[**21 καὶ λέγε—ὄντα**] is expunged by Herwerden, but the emphatic reiteration is in keeping with the whole tone of the passage. For the sense we may recall the words of the so-called oath of Hippo- crates εἰς οἰκίας δὲ ὁκόσας ἂν ἐσίω, ἐσελεύ- σομαι ἐπ’ ὠφελείῃ τῶν καμνόντων (Vol. I. p. 2 ed. Kühn).</ab>
<ab xml:id="097" ref="341d5">[**341 D 27 ἑκάστῳ τούτων:**] viz. τοῖς κάμ-</ab>
<ab xml:id="098" ref="342e8 342e9">[**342 E 34 ᾧ ἂν βλέπων.**] ᾧ is of course (τῷ) δ, and τῷ ἀρχομένῳ is also neuter (not masculine), like ἀρχομένου in D. Bremius took τῷ ἀρχομένῳ as mascu- line, and consequently changed (with in- ferior MS authority) πρὸς ἐκεῖνο into πρὸς ἐκείνῳ: he has been followed by Stall- baum and others. But as ᾧ must be neuter, it would be intolerable to make ἀρχομένῳ masculine, since both words (as denoting the same object) are covered by the same article, viz. τῷ before ἀρχομένῳ. ἐκείνῳ is of course neuter also.</ab>
<ab xml:id="099" ref="bookNoneNone">[**343 A—344 C** *Thrasymachus with much insolence of tone now abandons the idealistic point of view, and takes an ex- ample from experience. The shepherd does not, as a matter of fact, seek the good of his flock, but fattens them for his own or his master's advantage. In like manner it is their own advantage that is aimed at by rulers who deserve the name. Jus- tice is ‘other men’s good’ (ἀλλότριον ἀγα- θόν), whereas Injustice is one’s own: the just man comes off second best everywhere, alike in commercial and in political trans- actions. That it is far more to one’s interest to be unjust than to be just, we may see from the case of tyrants, who represent Injustice in its most perfect form. All men envy them. Finally, Thra- symachus reiterates his original theory with the remark that Injustice on a suffi- ciently large scale is at once stronger, more worthy of a freeman, and more masterly and commanding than Justice.*] 343 A-344 C</ab>
<ab xml:id="100" ref="book343a">[**343 A ff.**] It should be noted that Thrasymachus has in no way changed his theory, but only reverts to his original standpoint, that of experience. In the panegyric on Injustice in the present chapter, the new and important point is the appeal to the evidence of tyranny and the emotions which it roused in the mind of the Greeks. See on 344 B.</ab>
<ab xml:id="101" ref="343a1">[**2 εἰς τοὐναντίον.**] Justice has now become τὸ τοῦ ἥττονος (rather than κρείτ- τονος) συμφέρον.</ab>
<ab xml:id="102" ref="343a6">[**5 κορυζῶντα:**] ‘snivelling,’ μωραίνοντα, μυξάζοντα· κόρυζα γὰρ ἡ μῦξα, ἣν οἱ Ἀττικοὶ κορύζαν φασίν (Schol.). Ruhnken on *Timaeus Lex.* s.v. quotes among other passages Lucian *Alex.* § 20 ἦν δὲ τὸ μηχάνημα τοῦτο ἀνδρὶ μὲν οἴῳ σοι, εἰ δὲ μὴ φορτικὸν εἰπεῖν, καὶ οἴῳ ἐμοί, πρόδηλον καὶ γνῶναι ῥᾴδιον, τοῖς δὲ ἰδιώταις καὶ κορύζης μεστοῖς τὴν ῥῖνα τεράστιον καὶ πάνυ ἄπιστον ὅμοιον, and Horace *Sat.* I 4. 8 (of Lucilius) *emunctae naris*.</ab>
<ab xml:id="103" ref="343a7 343a8">[**6 ὅς γε αὐτῇ κτλ.**] “Apte αὐτῇ interpositum; nam ipsi nutrici Socratis insipientiam opprobrio esse, Thrasy- machus vult significare” Ast. Richter (*Fl. Jahrb.* for 1867 p. 140) ought not to have suggested ὅς γε αὐτός. The sense is ‘for she cannot teach you to recognise even sheep or shepherd,’ not ‘you do not know either sheep or shepherd’ (J. and C.), which would require οὔτε— οὔτε. The phrase is clearly a half-pro- verbial expression borrowed from the nursery.</ab>
<ab xml:id="104" ref="343a7">[**7 ὅτι οἴει τοὺς ποιμένας κτλ.**] Thra- symachus gives a new turn to the nursery saying. The illustration from the shep- herd and his sheep (which is now for the first time introduced) was used by the historical Socrates to justify the opposite conclusion (Xen. *Mem*. III 2. 1) ἐντυχὼν δέ ποτε στρατηγεῖν ἠρημένῳ τῳ, Τοῦ ἕνεκεν, ἔφη, Ὄμηρον οἴει τὸν Ἀγαμέμνονα προσαγορεῦσαι ποιμένα λαῶν; ἆρά γε ὅτι, ὥσπερ τὸν ποιμένα ἐπιμελεῖσθαι δεῖ, ὅπως σῶοί τε ἔσονται αἱ οἶες, καὶ τὰ ἐπιτήδεια ἕξουσιν, οὕτω καὶ τὸν στρατηγὸν ἐπιμε- λεῖσθαι δεῖ, ὅπως σῶοί τε οἱ στρατιῶται ἔσονται, καὶ τὰ ἐπιτήδεια ἕξουσι, καὶ οὐ πρὸς στρατιώτας οὕτω ἔσται? So also Arist. *Eth. Nic*. VIII 13. 1161ª 12 ff. εὖ γὰρ ποιεῖ τοὺς βασιλευομένους, εἴπερ ἀγαθὸς ὢν ἐπιμελεῖται αὐτῶν, ἵν᾽ εὖ πράττωσιν, ὥσπερ νομεὺς προβάτων· ὅθεν καὶ Ὅμηρος τὸν Ἀγαμέμνονα ποιμένα λαῶν εἴπεν.\n\nIn Plato *Pol*. 271 D ff. the deities of the golden age are compared to shepherds, and the comparison of a good ruler to a shepherd is very frequent in Plato: see Ast's *Lex. Plat*. s. v. νομεύς. In Socrates' view 'the shepherd careth for his sheep.' With Thrasymachus' attitude should be compared the picture of the tyrant in *Theaet*. 174 D as a συμβώτης ἢ ποιμένα ἤ τινα βουκόλον—πολὺ βδάδ- λοντα (he squeezes as much milk as he can out of his flock): also Solon ap. Arist. *Rep. Ath*. ch. 12 εἰ γὰρ τις ἄλλος ταύτης τῆς τιμῆς ἔτυχεν, οὐκ ἂν κατέσχε δῆμον οὐδ᾽ ἐπαύσατο, | πρὶν ἀνταράξας πίαρ ἐξεῖλεν γάλα. In the word ἀμοργοί or ἀμολγοί used by Cratinus in the sense of πόλεως ὄλεθροι (Meineke *Fr. Com. Graec*. II 1, p. 140) the image is the same. Compare the eloquent words of Ruskin in *Sesame and Lilies* § 43 and Milton's *Lycidas* 113—129.</ab>
<ab xml:id="105" ref="343b5 343b6">[**343 B 12 ἤγει διανοεῖσθαι.**] The conjecture διακεῖσθαι for διανοεῖσθαι is tempting in view of διατεθείη which follows, but διανοεῖσθαι is better suited to σκοπεῖν and βλέποντας just above. For the somewhat rare construction Schneider compares Laws 626 D αὐτῷ δὲ πρὸς αὐτὸν πότερον ὡς πολεμίῳ πρὸς πολε- μιον διανοητέον, ἢ πὸς ἔτι λέγομεν; and 628 D.</ab>
<ab xml:id="106" ref="343a2">[**15 πόρρω εἶ περί.**] πόρρω can hardly (I think) mean 'far from' (sc. knowing): this would require πόρρω εἶ <τοῦ τι εἰδέναι> περί, as Herwerden suggests: cf. *Lys*. 212 A οὕτω πόρρω εἰμὶ τοῦ κτήμα- τος ὥστε κτλ. The meaning is (I believe) 'so far on'; 'so profoundly versed are you in justice' etc.: cf. πόρρω ἤδη ἐστὶ τοῦ βίου *Ap*. 38 C and phrases like πόρρω σοφίας ἐλαύνειν: see also Blaydes on Ar. *Wasps* 192. Such biting sarcasm is appropriate in the mouth of Thrasy- machus.</ab>
<ab xml:id="107" ref="343c3">[**343 C 16 ἀλλότριον ἀγαθόν.**] Arist. *Eth. Nic*. V 3. 1130ª 3 f. διὰ δὲ τὸ τοῦτο τοῦτο καὶ ἀλλότριον ἀγαθὸν δοκεῖ εἶναι ἡ δικαιοσύνη μόνη τῶν ἀρετῶν, ὅτι πρὸς ἕτερόν ἐστιν· ἄλλῳ γὰρ τὰ συμφέροντα πράττει, ἢ ἄρχοντι ἢ κοινωνῷ (with Stewart's note) and *ib*. IX. 1134b 5.</ab>
<ab xml:id="108" ref="343c4">[**17 τῷ ὄντι**] is not τῷ ὄντι δικαίῳ, but revera (as Stallbaum observes).</ab>
<ab xml:id="109" ref="book344c">[**19 ὡς ἀληθῶς**] as well as ἀληθῶς, τῷ</ab>
<ab xml:id="110" ref="bookNoneNone">[**344 D—347 E** *The reply of Socrates falls into two parts. In the first* (344 D— 347 E), *after emphatically expressing his* *dissent from Thrasymachus’ views, and* *protesting against the Sophist’s retractation* *(in the example of the shepherd and his* *sheep) of the doctrine that every ruler seeks* *the good of his subjects, Socrates reverts* *to the stricter form of reasoning to which* *Thrasymachus had formerly challenged* *him, and points out that no rulers, proper* *ly so called, rule willingly: they require* *wages. When any kind of rule, e.g. an* *art, is attended with advantage to the ruler,* *the advantage comes from the concomitant* *operation of the ‘art of wage-earning,’* *and not from the rule itself. Medicine* *produces health; the art of wages, wages;* *the doctor takes his fee, not qua doctor, but* *qua wage-earner. Thus it is not the ruler,* *qua ruler, but the subjects, as was already* *said, who reap the advantage. The wages* *which induce a man to rule, may be money,* *or honour, or the prospect of a penalty if* *he should refuse. The most efficacious* *penalty, in the case of the best natures, is* *the prospect of being ruled by worse men* *than themselves. In a city of good men,* *freedom from office would be as eagerly* *sought for as office itself is now. Herewith* *ends for the present the refutation of the* *theory that Justice is the interest of the* *stronger. Socrates promises to resume the* *subject on another occasion.*] 344 D-347 E</ab>
<ab xml:id="111" ref="344d1 344d2 344d3 344d4 344d5 344d6 344d7">[**344 D ff.**] *The ensuing discussion is* *not a new argument* (see 345 C *ἔτι γὰρ* *τὰ ἔμπροσθεν ἐπισκεψώμεθα) *in support* *of Socrates’ view, but a restatement of* *his theory, with an addition necessitated* *by Thrasymachus’ example of the shep* *herd. The shepherd* (says Socrates) *is* *no shepherd, when he fattens his sheep* *for his own gain, nor the ruler a ruler,* *when he enriches himself at the expense* *of his subjects. On such occasions both* *shepherd and ruler are in reality* μισθω* *τικοί*—*professors of* μισθωτική, *an art* *which is distinct from that of ruling,* *though usually associated with it. This* *analysis is new and valuable in itself; it* *also enables Socrates* (in 347 D) *to make* *the first explicit allusion in the* Republic* *to an ideal state, and to formulate what* *afterwards becomes a leading principle of* *the Platonic commonwealth*—*the reluct* *ance of the ruling class to accept office.*</ab>
<ab xml:id="112" ref="344d2">[**344 D 24 καταντλήσας.**] *For the me* *taphor cf. infra* VII 536 B, *Lys*. 204 D, *Lucian* Dem. Enc. 16 (imitated from this *passage) *and other examples in Blaydes* *on Ar. Wasps* 483.</ab>
<ab xml:id="113" ref="344d6">[**28 ἐμβαλών:**] *cf. Theaet*. 165 D, *Prot*. 342 E. *The whole expression recalls the* *Latin proverb* scrupulum abeunti (Cic. de Fin. IV 80).</ab>
<ab xml:id="114" ref="344e2">[**344 E 31 διαγόμενος.**] *The use of this* *verb in Soph. El*. 782 *χρόνος διῆγέ με,* *Dem*. 18. 89 *πόλεμος*—*διῆγεν ὑμᾶς,* Xen. Rep. Lac. 1. 3 *and elsewhere is in favour* *of regarding* διαγόμενος (‘living’) *as gram* *matically passive and not middle both here* *and in* Laws 758 A. *Cf. Stephanus-Hase’* *Thes. s.v.* διάγω.</ab>
<ab xml:id="115" ref="344e4">[**ἐγὼ γὰρ κτλ.**] *I agree with Stallbaum* *and others in taking this sentence as* *interrogative: ‘do you mean that I* *think otherwise about this matter?’ i.e.* *think that it is not a question of* βίου διαγωγῇ. *J. and C. complain that this* *interpretation is “wanting in point.” It* *is surely much to the point to make Thra* *symachus repudiate the imputation of* *trifling. His doctrine appears all the more* *dangerous when he confesses that it is no* sophistic paradox, but a rule of life. I can see nothing to justify Apelt's con- jecture ἔγωγε ἀφ᾽ for ἐγὼ γὰρ (*Observ. Crit.* p. 11).</ab>
<ab xml:id="116" ref="344e5">[**33 ἤτοι ἡμῶν γε.**] ἤτοι or ἤτοι—γε= ‘or else’ (not ‘or rather’ as J. and C.). The regular construction is ἤτοι—ἤ, and ἤ—ἤτοι was condemned by the gram- marians as a solecism, though it occurs in Pind. *Nem*. 6. 5. With the use of ἤτοι in this passage cf. III 400 C, IV 433 A τοῦτό ἐστιν—ἤτοι τούτου τι εἶδος ἢ δικαιο- σύνη. Emendations have been suggested on all these passages of Plato: here ἤ τοι (van Prinsterer, Hartman) and in the other two passages ἤ: but we are not justified in altering the text. Cf. Kugler *de partic. τοι eiusque comp*. ap. *Pl*. usu p. 14.</ab>
<ab xml:id="117" ref="345a5 345a6">[**345 A 5 ἔστω μὲν ἄδικος κτλ.**] The subject is ὁ ἄδικος, supplied from ἀδικίαν. ἢ ἀδικία or τὸ ἀδικεῖν is the subject of ἔστι. The effect is exactly as in the English ‘let him be unjust’ etc., ‘never- theless he cannot convince me that it is really more profitable than justice.’ J. and C. understand τις before ἔστω, need- lessly, as I think, and suppose that the “supposed impunity of injustice” is the subject to πείθει, but πείθει is much better with a personal subject. Although the sentence is a trifle loose, it is clear enough, and there is no occasion for reading πεί- θεις (with Vind. D and Ficinus).</ab>
<ab xml:id="118" ref="345b5 345b6 345b7">[**345 B 12 ἐνθῶ.**] ἐντιθέναι (as Wohlrab points out) was used of nurses feeding children: cf. Ar. *Knights* 716 f., supra 343 A, and (for the general idea) Theognis 435 and Pl. *Symp*. 175 D. In μὰ Δία, μὴ σύ γε Socrates shudders at the prospect of having Thrasymachus for his intellectual nurse.</ab>
<ab xml:id="119" ref="345c4">[**345 C 17 ποιμαίνειν.**] See cr. n. Cobet (*Mnem*. IX p. 355) calls for ποιμαίνῃ, but the “addita verba καθ᾽ ὅσον ποιμήν ἐστιν</ab>
<ab xml:id="120" ref="346e8">[**346 E 33. ἔλεγον μηδένα ἐθέλειν.**] μή with the infinitive after verbs of saying, thinking and the like “carries with it the emphasis of the witness on oath, so to speak the emphasis of desire” (Gilder-sleeve in *A. J. Ph.* I 50). Cf. *Theaet.* 155 A, *Euthyph.* 6 B, *Phaed.* 94 C al., and infr. III 407 E, IV 419 A.</ab>
<ab xml:id="121" ref="347a2">[**347 A 2. ὡς ἔοικε**] belongs to ὧν ἕνεκα, and δεῖν is in indirect narration after ἔλεγον above. There would be no object in qualifying the force of δεῖν; it is not disputed that rulers must have their reward. Hence Stallbaum is wrong in regarding δεῖν as under the influence of ἔοικε, an illogical idiom which is common in Herodotus (Stein on I 65), and found occasionally in Tragedy (Jebb on *Trach.* 1238) and in Plato (*Phil.* 20 D, *Soph.* 263 D, *Euthyd.* 280 D). That ὡς ἔοικε has no influence on δεῖν in this passage may also be seen from the fact that δεῖν (not δέοι) would still be used if ὡς ἔοικε were removed. δεῖν is not for δέον; the late participial form δεῖν is not found in Plato: see my note on *Euthyph.* 4 D.</ab>
<ab xml:id="122" ref="347a4">[**4. ἄρχῃ.**] The transition from plural to singular and conversely is common: see for examples III 408 B, 411 C, 413 D, E, IV 426 A, C, V 463 D, VI 496 C, 500 C, VIII 554 A, C, 558 A, IX 591 A, X 601 D, E, 604 D, and cf. Heindorf on *Gorg.* 478 C, *Prot.* 319 D.</ab>
<ab xml:id="123" ref="347a7">[**7. ὡς ἐν μισθοῦ μέρει.**] ὡς is not (with Wohlrab) to be taken with ἐν μισθοῦ μέρει, but stands for the indirect interrogative ὅπως.</ab>
<ab xml:id="124" ref="347b7">[**347 B 14. αὐτοῖς**] = ‘by themselves,’ ‘ul-tro,’ should be construed with λαμβάνοντες. The conjecture αὐτόν for αὐτοῖς is very tame.</ab>
<ab xml:id="125" ref="347c2 347c3">[**347 C 16 ὅθεν κινδυνεύει—νενομίσθαι.**] These words are intended to indicate parenthetically that Socrates’ thesis finds support in the common judgment of men. Good men, he says, require to be compelled to rule. This may be why (ὅθεν) it is accounted a disgrace to enter on office willingly: that is to say, if you so do, you may be inferred to be, not ἀγαθός, but φιλότιμος or φιλάργυρος, which ὄνειδος λέγεται τε καὶ ἔστιν 347 B. There is no good reason for rejecting the clause, as some have proposed to do.</ab>
<ab xml:id="126" ref="347d2 347d3">[**347 D 23 πόλις ἀνδρῶν ἀγαθῶν**] is the first express allusion to an Ideal City in the *Republic*. The principle here laid down—the reluctance of the best men to undertake the task of government—is fully recognised in Plato’s commonwealth, where the ἄρχοντες are represented as unwilling to desert the life of contemplation for the cares of office. ‘Nolo episcopari’ is in fact one of the leading guarantees which Plato gives against the abuse of political power (Nohle *Die Staatslehre Plato’s in ihr. gesch. Entwick.* p. 119). See VI 520 E, 521 A, where this topic is resumed. Cf. also *Sesame and Lilies* § 43 “The true kings—rule quietly, if at all, and hate ruling; too many of them make ‘il gran rifiuto.’”</ab>
<ab xml:id="127" ref="347d5">[**25 τῷ ὄντι κτλ.**] τῷ ὄντι belongs to οὐ πέφυκε, not to ἀληθινός (as Ast sup- poses). Richter suggests ἀληθινῶς for ἀλη- θινός, but what is said of a single ruler applies to all: cf. (with Schneider) *Laws* 733 E λέγωμεν δὴ σώφρονα βίον ἕνα εἶναι καὶ φρόνιμον ἕνα καὶ ἕνα τὸν ἀνδρεῖον.</ab>
<ab xml:id="128" ref="347d6 347d7">[**26 πᾶς ἄν κτλ.**] The articular infinitive with αἱρεῖσθαι is hard to parallel, and on this ground Richards would cancel τό. I once thought that τὸ ὠφελεῖσθαι might be taken as the object after γιγνώσκων (‘he who knows what being benefited is,’ i.e. virtually ‘who knows his own interests’); but this is harsh, and I now acquiesce in the usual interpretation. With γιγνώσκων (*intellegens*) used absolutely cf. (with Schneider) *Laws* 733 E σώφρονα μὲν οὖν βίον ὁ γιγνώσκων θήσει πρᾶον ἐπὶ πάντα. For the sentiment cf. Soph. *O. T.* 584—598, Eur. *Ion* 621—632, Hipp. 1016—1020.</ab>
<ab xml:id="129" ref="347e2">[**347 E 30 εἰσαῦθις σκεψόμεθα.**] The reference has been much discussed. Pfleiderer’s idea (*Zur Lösung d. Pl. Fr.* p. 72) that the words were introduced by Plato “bei der Gesamtredaktion des Werkes” to prepare us for the second half of Book X is most unlikely, because (among other reasons) Book X does not expressly revert to this topic at all. Siebeck (*Zur Chron. d. Pl. Dialoge* pp. 121 ff.) holds that phrases of this sort always refer either to some future dialogue contemplated by Plato, or to a later part of the same dialogue. It is difficult to establish either alternative in the present case; nor</ab>
<ab xml:id="130" ref="book347e">[**ances of Thrasymachus on the nature of injustice are refuted by means of argu- ments which have an indirect bearing on the question at issue (see 352 D φαινονται μὲν οὖν καὶ νῦν, ὡς ἐμοὶ δοκεῖ, ἐξ ὧν εἰρήκαμεν· ὅμως δ᾽ ἔτι βέλτιον σκεπτέον). This part of Socrates' reply may therefore be regarded as itself subdivided into two parts—the first being an indirect, the second a direct refutation of Thrasyma- chus. Cf. 352 D n.**] ...ances of Thrasymachus on the nature of injustice are refuted by means of argu- ments which have an indirect bearing on the question at issue (see 352 D φαινονται μὲν οὖν καὶ νῦν, ὡς ἐμοὶ δοκεῖ, ἐξ ὧν εἰρήκαμεν· ὅμως δ᾽ ἔτι βέλτιον σκεπτέον). This part of Socrates' reply may therefore be regarded as itself subdivided into two parts—the first being an indirect, the second a direct refutation of Thrasyma- chus. Cf. 352 D n.</ab>
<ab xml:id="131" ref="348c7 348c10">[**348 C 17 εἰκός γε—τοὐναντίον.**] Thrasymachus' view of δικαιοσύνη is like Callicles' theory of ἀρετή in *Gorg*. 491 E ff. esp. 492 B τρυφὴ καὶ ἀκολασία καὶ ἐλευθερία, ἐὰν ἐπικουρίαν ἔχῃ, τοῦτ᾽ ἐστὶν ἀρετή τε καὶ εὐδαιμονία. The irony is clearly marked by ὦ ἥδιστε, and Hartman should not have revived Hirschig's pro- posal to read <οὐκοῦν> εἰκός γε.</ab>
<ab xml:id="132" ref="348c9">[**19 ἀλλὰ τί μήν?;**] ‘Well, what else?’ Cf. (with J. and C.) *Symp*. 206 E.</ab>
<ab xml:id="133" ref="348d1">[**348 D 20 πάνυ γενναίαν εὐήθειαν:**] ‘sublime simplicity.’ Such contempt for εὐήθεια recalls Thucydides' description of contemporary morals: cf. especially III 83. 1 καὶ τὸ εὐηθες, οὗ τὸ γενναῖον πλεῖστον μετέχει, καταγελασθὲν ἠφανίσθη.</ab>
<ab xml:id="134" ref="348d2 348d5">[**21 εὐβουλία**] was preeminently a po- litical virtue: cf. *Alc*. I 125 E πολιτείας κοινωνοῦντων τίνα καλεῖς ἐπιστήμην; Εὐ- βουλίαν ἔγωγε. *Prot*. 318 E, and infra IV 428 B. It is therefore fitly used by Thrasymachus to describe his theory, which is a theory of political rather than of private morality: cf. πόλεις τε—ποιεῖ- σθαι below.</ab>
<ab xml:id="135" ref="348d6">[**23 ὑφ᾽ ἑαυτοὺς ποιεῖσθαι.**] ἑαυτοὺς is found in some inferior MSS., but the ac- cusative is also admissible. Cf. Thuc. IV 60 (cited by Schneider) εἰκὸς—αὐτοὺς τάδε πάντα πειράσασθαι ὑπὸ σφᾶς ποιεί- σθαι. In τέλεως Thrasymachus recalls the τελέαν ἀδικίαν of 348 B.</ab>
<ab xml:id="136" ref="348d8">[**24 ἢ δ᾽ ὅς οἴει—λέγειν.**] Baiter (with Paris A) assigns these words to Socrates; but they come much more naturally from Thrasymachus: cf. 344 B. βαλλάντια and not βαλάντια is the spelling of A here and in VIII 552 D (βαλλαντιοστόμοι); in IX 575 B (βαλλαντιοτομοῦσι) the second λ is due to an early corrector. The double-λλ- has also the best MS authority in *Gorg*. 508 E, *Symp*. 190 E. See also Blaydes on *Ar. Frogs* 772. For ἢ δ᾽ ὅς below after ἔφη cf. *Phaed*. 78 A and VII 522 A.</ab>
<ab xml:id="137" ref="348e5">[**348 E 30 ἤδη στερεώτερον:**] ‘still more stubborn.’ στερεός is like σκληρός in *Theaet*. 155 E σκληροὺς—καὶ ἀντιτύπους ἀνθρώπους, but stronger, suggesting cast- iron hardness and inflexibility.</ab>
<ab xml:id="138" ref="348e6">[**ῥᾴδιον.**] See cr. n. Schneider refers to *Lysis* 217 A τὴν δὲ ἀληθεστάτην καὶ ἀρίστην ἰσότητα οὐκέτι ῥᾴδιον παντὶ ἰδεῖν. ῥᾴδιον is not (I think) possible here, and a scribe might easily omit ΙΔ in ΠΑΙΔΙΟΝ. Cf. *Introd*. § 5.</ab>
<ab xml:id="139" ref="348e6 348e7 348e8">[**31 εἰ γὰρ κτλ.**] Gorg. 483 C νόμῳ μὲν τοῦτο ἄδικον καὶ αἰσχρὸν λέγεται, τὸ πλέον ζητεῖν ἔχειν τῶν πολλῶν, καὶ ἀδικεῖν αὐτὸ καλοῦσιν. Dümmler (*Zur Comp. d.* *Pl. St.* p. 13) goes so far as to assert that ὥσπερ ἄλλοι τινές is an express reference to Polus in the *Gorgias*; but nothing is gained by so hazardous a conjecture.</ab>
<ab xml:id="140" ref="349a3">[**349 A 1 I προσετίθεμεν:**] ‘used to at- tribute to,’ sc. before you announced your view—with ironical deference, like ἐλέγομεν in *Prot.* 353 C τί οὖν φατε τοῦτο εἶναι, ὃ ἡμεῖς ἥττω εἶναι τῶν ἡδονῶν ἐλέγομεν; Stallbaum takes the im- perfect as referring to 345 C, but neither there nor in 348 C (cited by Schneider) is there anything to justify a particular reference.</ab>
<ab xml:id="141" ref="349a5 349a7">[**5 ἐμοὶ γὰρ—λέγειν.**] A similar re- mark is made after Callicles has ex- pounded kindred views in *Gorg.* 492 D σαφῶς γὰρ σὺ νῦν λέγεις ἃ οἱ ἄλλοι δια- νοοῦνται μέν, λέγειν δὲ οὐκ ἐθέλουσι.</ab>
<ab xml:id="142" ref="349a6">[**6 τὰ δοκοῦντα κτλ.**] can only mean ‘what you think about the truth,’ not ‘what you think to be the truth’ (D. and V.) or ‘your real mind’ (Schneider and Jowett). We should expect ἀδικίας for ἀληθείας, as H. Wolf proposed to read, for it is Injustice, not Truth, which is the subject of dispute. But as ἀδικίας has not a vestige of support from the MSS, I have not ventured to make the change. The truth in question must be understood as the truth about justice and injustice. Herwerden’s ἐπὶ τῆς ἀληθείας (for which he compares Dem. *de Cor.* 17, 226, and 294) will hardly command assent.</ab>
<ab xml:id="143" ref="349a9">[**Τί δέ—ἐλέγχει?;**] Cf. Charm. 161 C πάντως γὰρ οὐ τοῦτο σκεπτέον ὅστις αὐτὸ εἶπεν, ἀλλὰ πότερον ἀληθὲς λέγεται ἢ οὔ.</ab>
<ab xml:id="144" ref="349b10">[**349 B 10 πλέον ἔχειν.**] The literal and derived significations of this phrase are treated as identical throughout the curious reasoning which follows. Prima- rily, πλέον ἔχειν refers to quantitative superiority; in its derived sense, it is used (together with πλεονεκτεῖν) more generally of ‘overreaching.’</ab>
<ab xml:id="145" ref="349b6 349b7">[**11 τῆς δικαίας πράξεως.**] ‘To have more than the just action’ means ‘to do more than is just’ (cf. πλείω—αἱρεῖσθαι— πράττειν 350 A), outdo, overreach what is just in action. The notion of virtue as a μεσότης is implied.</ab>
<ab xml:id="146" ref="349b6 349b7">[**Οὐδὲ τῆς κτλ.**] See *cr. n.* I do not think that οὐδὲ τῆς δικαίας can be right. The whole emphasis (as οὐδὲ shews) must be on πράξεως, and the emphatic word should be expressed. οὐδὲ τῆς πράξεως τῆς δικαίας (sc. any more than the ἀνδρὸς δικαίου) gives exactly the emphasis re- quired. In the cases quoted by Schneider</ab>
<ab xml:id="147" ref="350c10 350c11">[**350 C 20 ἀναπέφανται.**] Stallbaum naively reminds us that ἀναπέφανται is often used of a conclusion which “praeter exspectationem emergit et elucet.” The pervading fallacy in the discussion is akin to the *a dicto secundum quid ad dictum simpliciter*. Thus ‘like’ and ‘unlike’ are used absolutely, and each of them is equated with itself. The wise man is held to be good, because one is good in that in which one is wise (this might how- ever be justified on the “stricter mode of reasoning”). Finally, the just man is inferred to be wise and good, on the principle that one is what one resembles: but whether the resemblance be in essence or in accident, we are not told. The argument should be regarded as a dia- lectical tour de force,—φιλόοικον μᾶλλον ἢ φιλάληθες. The reasoning in the next section of the argument strikes a deeper note.</ab>
<ab xml:id="148" ref="350c10 350c11">[**350 C—352 D**] Socrates now attacks the second assertion made by Thrasy- machus in 349 A, viz. that Injustice is strong. Justice (he argues) is stronger than Injustice, both because it is (as we have seen) virtue and wisdom, and be- cause in its effects it is the antithesis of Injustice, which infuses hatred and se- dition, both into aggregates of individuals, and into the individual himself. In- justice weakens by preventing community of action; it makes men collectively and individually hateful to themselves and to the just, among whom are the gods. When Injustice seems to be strong, it is in virtue of some latent Justice which it still re- tains.</ab>
<ab xml:id="149" ref="350c1 350c2 350c3 350c4 350c5 350c6 350c7 350c8 350c9 350c10 350c11 350c12">[**350 c ff.**] The argument in this section has a deeper ethical import than any which has preceded, and foreshadows some of the central doctrines of the *Republic*. See notes on 351 D, E, and (for the importance of the whole discus- sion in the general history of philosophy) Bosanquet’s *Companion*, p. 63, where it is justly observed that the argument “marks an era in philosophy. It is a first reading of the central facts of society, morality, and nature. In social analysis it founds the idea of organization and division of la- bour. In morality it gives the concep- tion of a distinctively human life which is the content or positive end of the dis- tinctively human will. And for natural knowledge it suggests the connection be- tween function and definition, and con- sequently between purpose and reality, which is profoundly developed in the sixth and seventh books. These concep- tions become corner-stones of Aristotle’s Philosophy, and still, when seen in their connection, form the very core of the best thought.”</ab>
<ab xml:id="150" ref="350c12">[**22 δ δὲ Θρασύμαχος κτλ.**] ‘Now Thrasymachus’ etc. δέ is not “flat” (Tucker), but at least as good as δή, and much better supported by the mss.</ab>
<ab xml:id="151" ref="350c12">[**οὐχ ὡς ἐγὼ νῦν ῥᾳδίως λέγω.**] “Ex- pectabam certe: οὐχ ὡς ἐγὼ νῦν λέγω ῥᾳδίως,” says Herwerden; but the ante- cedent in Greek is idiomatically attracted into the relative clause (Kühner *Gr. Gramm*. II p. 922). Translate ‘not in the easy way in which I now repeat them.’</ab>
<ab xml:id="152" ref="350d2 350d3">[**350 D 24 ἅτε καὶ θέρους ὄντος.**] The action is probably laid in Hecatom- baeon (roughly our July): see *Introd*. § 3. Bekker (following the punctuation of A) takes *τότε* with *οὕτως*, but *οὕτως* δὲ *οὕπω* shews that it belongs to *καὶ εἶδον*. *τότε καὶ* is simply 'then too'; I cannot see anything "mock-heroic" in the expression, as J. and C. do.</ab>
<ab xml:id="153" ref="350e2 350e3">[**350 E 32 ὥσπερ ταῖς γραυσίν.**] Cf. Gorg. 527 A *τάχα δ᾽ οὖν ταῦτα μῦθος σοι δοκεῖ λέγεσθαι, ὥσπερ γραὸς, καὶ κατα- φρονεῖς αὐτῶν*: Pol. 268 E *ἀλλὰ δὴ τῷ μύθῳ μου πάνυ πρόσεχε τὸν νοῦν, καθάπερ οἱ παῖδες*. *ταῖς* for *ταῖς* was read before Ast on the authority of one MS; but *ταῖς* is quite satisfactory.</ab>
<ab xml:id="154" ref="350d7 350d8">[**37 ὅπερ ἄρτι.**] The words *ἔφαμεν δὲ δὴ καὶ ἰσχυρὸν εἶναι τὴν ἀδικίαν* ἢ *οὐ μέμνησαι*? (350 D), which are referred to in *ἄρτι*, involve the general question of the relation between justice and injustice; whence we have *ὁποῖόν τι τυγχάνει ὂν δικαιοσύνη πρὸς ἀδικίαν*. *ὁποῖον* depends on *ἐρωτῶ*, not on *λόγον*.</ab>
<ab xml:id="155" ref="351a1 351a2">[**351 A 2 ἐλέχθη γάρ που:**] 344 C, 348 E. It has nowhere been expressly said that Injustice is *δυνατώτερον* than Justice, but *καὶ δυνατώτερον* is added for emphasis (see on *ἢ λέγειν* in 350 A); and indeed according to the theory of Thra- symachus *δύναμις* (power in a general sense) rests solely on *ἰσχύς* (physical strength). *δύναμις* and *ἰσχύς* are clearly distinguished in Prot. 351 A.</ab>
<ab xml:id="156" ref="351a5">[**6 ἁπλῶς.**] The Platonic use of *ἁπλοῦν* has been investigated by Bonitz in Hermes II (1867) pp. 307 ff. Its antitheses are *σύνθετον, διάφορον, σύμβολον, πεπλεγμένον, ποικίλον*, and the like, and it denotes that which is uniform, or single and simple, or true without any difference or qualifi- cations. *ἁπλῶς οὕτως* means merely 'in this simple or general way' ('im Allge- meinen' Schneider); a more elaborate and profounder proof (thinks Socrates) is necessary.</ab>
<ab xml:id="157" ref="352b5 352b6">[**352 B 11 τὰ λοιπὰ κτλ.:**] viz. the discussion which begins in D below.</ab>
<ab xml:id="158" ref="352b6 352b7 352b8">[**12 ὅτι μὲν γὰρ κτλ.**] The whole sentence is summed up in ταῦτα μὲν οὖν ὅτι οὕτως ἔχει (352 D) and placed in this recapitulated form under the government of μανθάνω. The introduction of the antithesis (ἀλλὰ δὴ κτλ.) to οἱ δὲ ἄδικοι οὐδὲν πράττειν μετ’ ἀλλήλων οἷοί τε, and of the explanations required by that antithesis, complicates the sentence, without, however, rendering it obscure. For similar anacolutha with ὅτι see V 465 A, VI 493 D nn. and cf. Engelhardt *Anac. Plat. Spec.* III pp. 38, 40. The whole sentence forms a kind of transition to “the rest of the feast” by summing up what has been so far proved; viz. that Justice is wisdom and virtue (καὶ σοφώτεροι καὶ ἀμείνους), and more capable of action than Injustice (δυνατώτεροι πράττειν); even the difficulty raised in ἀλλὰ δὴ—ἀδύνατοι is not new, having been briefly explained in 351 C. Lieb- hold’s ἔτι for ὅτι is an unhappy suggestion; nor should ὅτι be rendered ‘quoniam,’ as Hartman proposes.</ab>
<ab xml:id="159" ref="352c5">[**352 C 18 μήτοι—γε:**] a strong nega- tive somewhat rarely used by Plato: cf. *Phil.* 67 A and *infra* III 388 B, C. See Kugler *de part. rei eiusque comp. ap. Pl.* usu p. 11.</ab>
<ab xml:id="160" ref="bookNoneNone">[**352 D—354 C** *The argument here reverts to 347 E, and the rest of the book offers a direct refutation of the view that Injustice is more advantageous than Justice, in other words, that the life of the unjust man is better than that of the just. An indirect refutation, says Socrates, is afforded by the recent discussion (from 348 B to 352 D); the direct is as follows. *Everything has its peculiar work or pro- duct* (ἔργον) *that, namely, which it alone produces, or which it produces better than aught else. Everything moreover has its own peculiar excellence, without which it will not do its work well. Now the work of soul is to deliberate, to rule, to live: its excellence is Justice. Therefore the just soul will live well, and to live well is to be blest and happy. And as this is more advantageous than to be miserable, In- justice can never be more advantageous than Justice. In conclusion, Socrates sums up regretfully: until we know what Justice is, we are not likely to discover whether it is a virtue or a vice, and whether its possessor is happy or un- happy*.] 352 D-354 C</ab>
<ab xml:id="161" ref="352d9">[**352 D ff.**] The view that everything has its own peculiar function, which it can perform better than anything else, afterwards becomes one of the cardinal principles of the Ideal State (II 369 E ff.); and the statement that everything has an excellence or virtue of its own is reaffirmed in Book x, where we are also told that everything has its own peculiar vice, that of soul being ἀδικία (608 B ff.).</ab>
<ab xml:id="162" ref="352d6">[**27 ὅντινα τρόπον χρὴ ζῆν.**] A remi-niscence of the πῶς βιωτέον of Socrates: cf. **Euthyd.** 272 B.</ab>
<ab xml:id="163" ref="352e3">[**352 E 30 ὃ ἂν—ἄριστα.**] The poli-tical applications of this principle are developed from II 369 B onwards: cf. IV 433 A ff.</ab>
<ab xml:id="164" ref="352e7">[**32 ἀκούσαις κτλ.**] The rapid succes-sion of questions makes it possible to dispense with ἂν in the second: cf. II 382 E.</ab>
<ab xml:id="165" ref="352e9">[**33 φαῖμεν.**] See *cr. n.* If φαμέν is retained, ἂν will belong to εἶναι (cf. VI 493 C), but it is inappropriate here to make εἶναι future or hypothetical. Schneider, while retaining φαμέν, refers ἂν to δικαίως, “*ut sensus sit: οὐκοῦν, εἰ ταῦτα τούτων φαῖμεν ἔργα εἶναι, δικαίως* ἂν φαῖμεν”—a harsh and unnatural view. We may either drop ἂν and keep φαμέν, as (with one of Stobaeus’ MSS *Flor.* 9. 63) I formerly did: or change φαμέν to φαῖμεν. The latter solution is easier and better. Similarly in φαῖμεν below 353 B the ι is due to A². See also *Introd.* § 5.</ab>
<ab xml:id="166" ref="353a9 353a10">[**353 A 1 ἀποτέμοις**] —see *cr. n.*—can hardly, I think, dispense with the particle ἂν. It should be noted that the illustra-tions are of two kinds—the first to illustrate ἢ μόνῳ ἐκείνῳ, the second to illustrate ἄριστα; after each division the conclusion is stated, in the second case more diffidently (ἀρ᾽ οὖν οὐ—θήσομεν), perhaps because it is less obvious.</ab>
<ab xml:id="167" ref="353a9 353a10">[**6 μόνον τι.**] Cornarius unhappily suggested τις for τι and Stephanus μόνῳ τις for μόνον τι (cf. 352 E). μόνον τι is of course the subject to ἀπεργάζηται.</ab>
<ab xml:id="168" ref="353b2 353b3">[**353 B 9 οὐκοῦν—προστέτακται.**] Cf.</ab>
<ab xml:id="169" ref="354b2">[**354 B 10 παραφερομένου.**] Casaubon's conjecture παραφερομένου is neat, but in- appropriate, the reference being to the successive courses at a feast, which were not usually carried round among the Greeks. In Athens IV 33 the carrying round of viands is mentioned as an Egyp- tian custom: *τρίτη δ᾽ ἐστὶν ἰδέα δείπνων αἰγυπτιακή, τραπεζῶν μὲν οὐ παρατιθε- μένων, πινάκων δὲ περιφερομένων*.</ab>
<ab xml:id="170" ref="354b3 354b4">[**II ἐγώ μοι δοκῶ κτλ.**] Lys. 222 E *δέομαι οὖν ὥσπερ οἱ σοφοὶ ἐν τοῖς δικαστη- ρίοις, τὰ εἰρημένα ἅπαντα ἀναπεμπάσασθαι*. The tone of the concluding summary recalls the usual finish of the earlier and professedly negative Socratic dialogues, like the *Charmides* (175 B—176 A). The only section of the dialogue which So- crates passes over in silence is the refuta- tion of the statement that Injustice is strong (350 D—352 C). The original question—the *quid sit* of Justice—is a- bandoned at 347 E; the *quale sit* occupies the rest of the dialogue, and Socrates enquires first whether Justice is vicious and ignorant, or wise and good (347 E— 350 C), next whether it is strong or weak (350 D—352 C), and lastly whether it is more or less advantageous than Injustice (352 D—354 A). To speculate on the *quid sit* of a thing before determining its *quid sit* is condemned by Plato in *Men*. 71 B *ὃ δὴ μὴ οἶδα τί ἐστι, πῶς ἂν ὁποῖόν γε τι εἰδείην*? cf. *ibid*. 86 D and 100 B. The words with which the first book concludes lead us to expect that in the remaining books the problem will be discussed in proper logical order—the essence first, and afterwards the quality, of Justice. The expectation is duly fulfilled; and Book I is therefore in the full sense of the term a *προοίμιον* to the whole work.</ab>
</div>
</body>
    </text>
</TEI>
